<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Check to debauchery, and other crying sins of these times with several useful rules for the attaining the contrary virtue : to which are annexed some directions and heads for meditation and prayer, taken out of Holy Scripture ... Oct. 26. 92 ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37316</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D51</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23020</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12062257</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12062257</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53294</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37316)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53294)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 865:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Check to debauchery, and other crying sins of these times with several useful rules for the attaining the contrary virtue : to which are annexed some directions and heads for meditation and prayer, taken out of Holy Scripture ... Oct. 26. 92 ...</title>
                  <author>L. D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 149, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Butt ... :</publisher>
                  <publisher>and are to be sold by Randal Taylor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Epistle to the Reader, signed L.D.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to L.D. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Table of contents: p. [11]-[16]</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin.</term>
               <term>Atonement.</term>
               <term>Prayer-books.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:53294:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53294:1"/>
            <p>A CHECK TO <hi>Debauchery,</hi> AND OTHER CRYING SINS Of theſe TIMES. WITH Several uſeful Rules for the attaining the contrary Virtues: To which are annexed ſome Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Heads for <hi>Meditation</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> taken out of <hi>Holy Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Except the Lord had left unto us a very ſmall Remnant, we ſhould have been as <hi>Sodom,</hi> and we ſhould have been like unto <hi>Gomorrah.</hi> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſ. 1.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Oct. 26. 92.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Imprimatur</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Edm. Bohun.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Butt</hi> in <hi>Princes-ſtreet</hi> near <hi>Covent-Garden;</hi> and are to be ſould by <hi>Randal Taylor</hi> near <hi>Stacioners-Hall.</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:53294:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53294:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER TO A FRIEND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I make you this ſmall Preſent, as knowing a <hi>Gentleman</hi> ought to be as zealous for <hi>Virtue</hi> as he is for <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour;</hi> and to ſhew his Courage chiefly in conquering himſelf. Your Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple influences very far, being ſo well known, and ſo well beloved: And I need not tell you how many, out of meer Emulation, are apt enough to become your <hi>Creatures</hi> and <hi>Followers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Converſation of ſome <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> is not ſo innocent as becomes their Quality, and as it ought to be: But it is commonly either <hi>Drollery,</hi> or,
<pb facs="tcp:53294:3"/>
               <hi>hard drinking.</hi> In the former, they neither ſpare Friend nor Foe; have no regard to Modeſty or good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and many times not to ſacred Things themſelves: And in the latter they are obnoxious to all other, even the greateſt Sins. It is <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation concerning Drunkenneſs, that it leads to Whoredom and all Lewd things, and renders Men more inſenſible than Beaſts; and yet (ſo great is the ſottiſhneſs of its followers) they will ſeek it ſtill and not refrain; <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.33. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thoſe falſe Maxims ſo much in Vogue with ſome, <hi>God will deal with me as a Gentleman, a Souldier, a Courtier</hi> and the like, ſo often urged in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe of a Vicious Life, were invented by the Common Enemy of Mankind to juſtle out the Laws of God, and to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all good Inſtructions of Pious Men ineffectual. Whereas the H. Scripture aſſures us, <hi>That God is no reſpecter of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but in every Nation he that feareth God and worketh Righteouſneſs [i. e.</hi> becomes and does the duty of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian]
<pb facs="tcp:53294:3"/>
               <hi>is accepted of him and none others; Acts</hi> 10.34, 35. <hi>John</hi> 3.18. And if we profeſs to know God, and deny him in our Works, we are no better than Infidels; and if we ſay we do know him and not keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments we are Lyars, let our Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or Station be what it will. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16.</p>
            <p>Many Saints now in Heaven, were indeed, not always ſo upon Earth; but then reſolutely reforming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and retracting their paſt Courſe of Life (the Divine Grace and aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance being never wanting to ſuch) they afterwards by inceſſant vertue became great Inſtruments of God's Glory in the Salvation of innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Souls. This is more or leſs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to every Man whilſt he lives in this World; who hath always ſome fault or other (if not ill habit) to retract, which by God's aſſiſtance he may do when he pleaſes; and it is his greateſt wiſdom not to delay his Endeavours, as the contrary his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt folly. I hope therefore you will not think me your Enemy becauſe I
<pb facs="tcp:53294:4"/>
tell you the truth: Who am on the contrary, <hi>Sir,</hi> Your Faithful Friend in this higheſt point of Friendſhip, and moſt ready to ſerve you in any thing conducing to your eternal happineſs, at leaſt my poor Prayers ſhall not be wanting</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Sincere Humble Servant. <hi>L. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:53294:4"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe Collections were deſigned chiefly for the good of my ſelf and ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Freinds, but may perhaps be of ſervice towards the awakening and exciting others to endeavour the pulling down thoſe abominable ſins which walk our Streets at Noon day, with a Whores forehead un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masked; and inhabit with us in our very Gates, even in the moſt Eminent and moſt frequented places of our Cities, without any notice taken of them, unleſs it be to Careſs and Encourage them.</p>
            <p>The wiſer Heathen would have thought ſuch groſs ſins a reproach to Reaſon, and
<pb facs="tcp:53294:5"/>
a Diſgrace to Humane Nature; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for Chriſtians to ſpend their whole lives here in them, and expect Heaven at the laſt (which is the reward only of Vertue and Holineſs) would be the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt folly and madneſs in the World. The way to Salvation is now by Grace, not by weak Nature; by what is revealed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to be the will of God, not what we can think, or can know any other way; by Faith, the evidence of things not ſeen by the Light of Nature, yet moſt certain to us, not by ſight or blind Reaſon; by denying, not pleaſing our ſelves. <hi>Paradiſe</hi> is not to be gained the ſame way it was loſt, but the contrary: Not by eating, but by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing to eat the forbidden Fruit. Not that ceaſing to do evil is ſufficient to make us happy, unleſs we alſo learn to do well; we muſt beſides bridling our Appetites, perform ſuch dayly duty to God as he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of us: Go on from Grace to Grace, from Vertue to Vertue, from one degree of Holineſs to another, till we come to the meaſure of the Stature of the fulneſs of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:53294:5"/>The firſt and principal ſtep however to Vertue is the ceaſing to be Vicious; and this cannot be done without renouncing all ſenſuality, and ſubduing our Luſts. In order to which we are to pray for the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of God's Grace, to conſult good Men and good Books, and reſolve to follow their Example and Directions: And if this ſhort Treatiſe ſhould conduce any thing towards the reclaiming of but one ſingle Sinner from a lewd, ſenſual, debauched Courſe of Life, to become a ſober, chaſt, ſincere Chriſtian, it would be thought more then a ſufficient recompence to</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
               <signed>Your Faithful Freind for the Good of your Soul. <hi>L. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:53294:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53294:6"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>OF Groſs Carnal Sins in General. <hi>Pag.</hi> 1</item>
                  <item>Marriage a lawful Remedy. <hi>Pag.</hi> 3</item>
                  <item>And ſo alſo our Lord's Counſel of a Single Life. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The practice of the preſent Age too contrary to both. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Of the impurity and filthineſs of ſuch ſins. <hi>Pag.</hi> 6</item>
                  <item>They proceed wholly from our ſelves. <hi>Pag.</hi> 7</item>
                  <item>Natural Infirmities no ſins. <hi>Pag.</hi> 6</item>
                  <item>Oppoſite to God's own Holineſs. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A particular mark ſet upon them in Scripture. <hi>Pag.</hi> 8</item>
                  <item>Oppoſite to the cleanneſs and ſanctity which ought to be in the Body as well as in the Soul of every Chriſtian. <hi>Pag.</hi> 9</item>
                  <item>Diſeaſes, Sores, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not the uncleanneſs her meant. <hi>ibid,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Body, the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt, a Member of Chriſt, his Spouſe, purchaſed with his precious Blood, therefore to be kept holy. <hi>Pag.</hi> 10, 11.</item>
                  <item>Fornication, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Diſhonourable and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graceful to the committors thereof. Offers the greateſt indignity to Chriſt's Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Pag.</hi> 12</item>
                  <item>Filthy Diſcourſe tending thereunto to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Natural ſhame accompanies ſuch ſins. <hi>Pag.</hi> 14</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:53294:7"/>The Habit thereof changes Men into Beaſts. <hi>Pag.</hi> 15</item>
                  <item>Theſe were the ſins the Heathen ſell into when abandoned by God for their Idolatry. <hi>Pag.</hi> 15, 16</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Of the puniſhments of ſuch ſins. <hi>Pag.</hi> 17</item>
                  <item>God a revenges of ſuch ſins himſelf. <hi>Pag.</hi> 18</item>
                  <item>Puniſhments dreadfel and ſudden. <hi>Pag.</hi> 19</item>
                  <item>Flood, Fire and Brimſtone, Sword, Loſs of Kingdoms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and what exceeds them all, eternal Death. <hi>Pag.</hi> 19, 20, 21</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Of the chaſtity of Marriage and of the purity of a Single Life. <hi>Pag.</hi> 23, 68</item>
                  <item>Marriage very honourable, compared to that, of Chriſt with his Church. <hi>Pag.</hi> 24</item>
                  <item>Many degrees of Conjugal chaſtity <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Some abſtain for a ſhorter time upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſome Solemn Devotion, Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating, <hi>&amp;c. Pag.</hi> 24, 25</item>
                  <item>Some longer for good ends alſo. <hi>Pag.</hi> 25, 26</item>
                  <item>Some their whole life (by conſent) for the better ſerving of God. <hi>Pag.</hi> 26, 27</item>
                  <item>Of a Single Life's being, 1ſt. more pure than chaſt Marriage it ſelf. <hi>Pag.</hi> 27, 28, 29</item>
                  <item>2ly. Freer from Worldly diſtractions, &amp;c. <hi>Pag.</hi> 29, 30</item>
                  <item>More ſenſible of God's preſence. <hi>Pag.</hi> 34</item>
                  <item>The Gift of Continency attainable by all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere endeavourers. <hi>Pag.</hi> 35, 36</item>
                  <item>Fitter for Contemplation. <hi>Pag.</hi> 33, 36.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:53294:7"/>More Heroical <hi>Pag.</hi> 37</item>
                  <item>The reward in Heaven greater. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of the purity of the Soul. <hi>Pag.</hi> 38</item>
                  <item>The ſins more immediately oppoſed, Pride, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with the Remedies, Humility, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> only barely named. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A blind Underſtanding and perverſe Will the cauſes. <hi>Pag.</hi> 39</item>
                  <item>Rebellion according to St. <hi>Judes</hi> Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Pag.</hi> 39, 40</item>
                  <item>Some Rules for the preventing and curing the ſins of the Fleſh. <hi>Pag.</hi> 41, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>The firſt Rule, of our Affectiens, <hi>&amp;c. Pag.</hi> 42</item>
                  <item>Of th Paſſion of Love. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>If wrong placed ruins us. <hi>Pag.</hi> 44.</item>
                  <item>If rightly placed makes us happy. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of the Memory and Imagination <hi>Pag.</hi> 41</item>
                  <item>The Store-houſe of the Soul <hi>Pag.</hi> 46</item>
                  <item>When advantageous. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>When Deſtructive to us. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The outward Senſes muſt be watched <hi>Pag.</hi> 47</item>
                  <item>Several ways of getting rid of Temptations from them, by meditating upon our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Paſſion, the 4 laſt things, <hi>&amp;c. Pag.</hi> 48, 49, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>The Second Rule, Of Suggeſtions. <hi>Pag.</hi> 52</item>
                  <item>Whence they proceed. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>What to be done if they tempt to habitual ſin. <hi>Pag.</hi> 53</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:53294:8"/>Uſing external Actions. <hi>Pag.</hi> 54</item>
                  <item>Delaying the Execution <hi>bid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Concerning ſtrong reſolutions <hi>Pag.</hi> 53, 54</item>
                  <item>Reſolutions Conditional upon a Forfeiture <hi>Pag.</hi> 56</item>
                  <item>Reſolution of returning and repenting upon a relapſe. <hi>Pag.</hi> 58</item>
                  <item>Telling the Temptation to ſome other. <hi>Pag.</hi> 60, 61</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>The third Rule, The Occaſions of Luſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be avoided. <hi>Pag.</hi> 62</item>
                  <item>1ſt. No making proviſion for the Fleſh to, <hi>&amp;c. ib.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Temperance in meat and drink. <hi>Pag.</hi> 63, 64, 65, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Frequent faſtings <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Moderate ſleep and ſometimes watchings, <hi>Pag.</hi> 66, 67</item>
                  <item>2ly: Lewd Company to be avoided, <hi>Pag.</hi> 70</item>
                  <item>No converſing with ſuch, <hi>Pag.</hi> 71</item>
                  <item>This for our own ſecurity and their good, <hi>Pag.</hi> 73</item>
                  <item>No eating, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with them when obſtinate, <hi>ibid</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Caſes of Neceſſity excepted, <hi>&amp;c. Pag.</hi> 74</item>
                  <item>The Church in her Councils and Canons very ſtrict in this matter, <hi>Pag.</hi> 75</item>
                  <item>Lewd Books alſo dangerous Companions <hi>Pag.</hi> 75</item>
                  <item>Good ones the beſt Companions in the World <hi>Pag.</hi> 76</item>
                  <item>3ly. Infamous places to be avoided <hi>ibid</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Whether ſingle houſes or whole cities, <hi>Pag.</hi> 77</item>
                  <item>No cohabiting with lewd Perſons, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A caution concerning Diſcourſes, <hi>Pag.</hi> 79, 80, 81</item>
                  <item>Eſpecially in much Company, <hi>ibid</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:53294:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>The fourth Rule. Of Divine Aſſiſtances, <hi>&amp;c. Pag.</hi> 82</item>
                  <item>Three things prenoted. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The firſt Grace given at Baptiſm. <hi>Pag.</hi> 83</item>
                  <item>More added upon our uſing the firſt well, <hi>Pag.</hi> 85</item>
                  <item>Of the Grace of Charity or the love of God. <hi>Pag.</hi> 86, 87</item>
                  <item>The force of Spiritual Gifts againſt the Fleſh, <hi>Pag.</hi> 89</item>
                  <item>How to Experience the good of Chriſtianity, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of frequent Examination of Conſcience. <hi>Pag.</hi> 90</item>
                  <item>The Subtility of the Devil. <hi>Pag.</hi> 92</item>
                  <item>2ly. The means of obtaining divine aſſiſtances, <hi>Pag.</hi> 93</item>
                  <item>1ſt. Prayer, Repentance, <hi>Pag.</hi> 93, 94, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2ly. Frequent Communicating, <hi>Pag.</hi> 98, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Summ of the whole. <hi>Pag.</hi> 102</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Some ſhort Directions and Heads for <hi>Meditation,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>OF Meditation, its Requiſites, and how it differs from Contemplation. <hi>Pag.</hi> 105</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:53294:9"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Of the Subject of Meditation, with Heads for the firſt Week. <hi>Pag.</hi> 111</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Heads of Meditation for the Second, Third, and Fourth Weeks. <hi>Pag.</hi> 121</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Meditations for the Fifth Week. <hi>Pag.</hi> 130</item>
                  <item>The Letany of Chriſtian Vertues, taken out of the Holy Scriptures. <hi>&amp;c. Pag.</hi> 139</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53294:9"/>
            <head>A CHECK TO DEBAUCHERY.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of groſſe Carnal Sins in General.</head>
               <p>THE ſpiritual Man, and good Chriſtian, hath no greater Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies than thoſe he carrieth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with him; his own depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Appetites and inordinate Deſires, eſpecially to ſenſual Pleaſure and carnal Delights, for which Fleſh and Blood ſo ſtrongly plead. Theſe, the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and the leſs heeded they are, ſo much the more dangerous to, and more deſtructive of, the Soul. There are no
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53294:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Temptations ſo vigorouſly aſſault us, or ſo eaſily beguile us as theſe: Which are therefore ſaid by the Prophet to ſeize and <hi>take away the Heart;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.11.</note> and the Deſire of them entreaſeth the more we deſcend to a particular thinking or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſing of them, even tho it be with a deſign to leave them. They make ſo ſtrong an Impreſſion, have ſo much of Force and Stratagem together, that there is no Conquering of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>em by our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending with them, but by our running away from them: So many wiles and ſecret devices; ſo many promiſes and ſpecious pretences; ſo many windings and turnings which the Wiſe Man calls the <hi>way of a Serpent upon a Rock,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.19.</note> 
                  <hi>the way of a Man with a Maid,</hi> that it is next to impoſſible to find them out: And that, becauſe, 1. Being born in Sin our very Nature is depraved: And, 2. inbred Luſt, when not ſubdued in us, ſo Captivates and Incarnates the Soul as to reſtrain its liberty of Reaſoning or thinking upon any thing elſe. This therefore is the greateſt Temptation, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53294:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the vanquiſhing of it, the great perfection of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Hence it is that Almighty, God in pity to frail man, hath provided him (whoſoever likes not to follow our Lord's Counſel of a ſingle life) a lawful remedy of his Luſts by Marriage;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 19 12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.2.</note> upon condition he live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bounds of it, and not endeavour the ſatiating his deſires any other way, or with any other Perſon than his own Wife. But alas, how contrary to this is the practice of the preſent Age, wherein a Vertuous ſingle Life is almoſt grown Scandalous; and Marriage will hardly be allowed to be Honourable, ſave only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of Legitimating Heirs and keeping up Families. Nay is it not rather reckoned as more Gentile, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Perſons of Quality (to their ſhame and diſhonour be it ſpoken) to have variety of Miſſes (as they are pleaſed to call their lewd Proſtitutes) tho themſelves, perhaps, very well mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried? And then, amongſt others of leſs plentiful Fortunes, Marriage (tho ſtiled
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53294:11"/>
by the Holy Ghoſt Honourable) is look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon as a mean and deſpicable thing, and little leſs than utter undoing: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, forſooth, they cannot then ſo near equal their Betters, their elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the like, in Eating and Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Cloaths, and other Formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of worldly Grandeur. Whereas now they can live without Care, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſort of Seriouſneſs; keep what the World calls the beſt Company; have their choice of Women and Wine, and deny themſelves nothing of Senſuality: And all this (as the World now goes) without running any great Hazard of loſing their Reputation; but not of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their immortal Souls, which ſure ought moſt to be regarded by them.</p>
               <p>To theſe ſupine Chriſtians, and Slaves to their own Luſts, who know better, but yet, as it were in their own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, take the Liberty, not only of living Counter to, but alſo of drolling upon, all that is ſerious or ſacred (even the Holy Scriptures, and our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour himſelf) rather than be ſtopp'd or check'd in their Career, or in the leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53294:11"/>
hindred the following the full Swinge of their own unbridled Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, and ungovernable Wits, I can only propoſe; <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Impurity and Filthineſs of ſuch Sins; and, <hi>Secondly,</hi> The ſevere Puniſhments that inſeparably attend them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:53294:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Impurity and Filthineſs of ſuch Sins.</head>
               <p>PAſſions, Frailties, and Infirmities, are the common Plea and Pretence of Sinners: Whereas the defect and proneneſs of our Nature to ſin, is in it ſelf no Sin, ſo long as not compli'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; and beſides, is abundantly repaired, and ſupernatural Aſſiſtance recovered by the Incarnation of our Saviour, and the Means he hath afforded us to a holy Life, if we are not wanting in the Application. The loſs of our Innocency hath not deprived us of any of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties. Our Underſtanding and Will are ſtill the ſame, and we have the ſame freedom to chuſe the Good and reject the Evil; nor is the divine Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance (God be thanked) denied to any that ſeek it. So that the Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53294:12"/>
of Sin is entirely from our ſelves, (<hi>Perditio tua ex te, Thy De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction is from thy ſelf,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.9.</note> ſays the Prophet) and the preventing of it wholly in our own power. And one would think we ſhould not readily fall in love with ſo great deformity. My preſent Subject however is, thoſe groſſer Sins, the Sins of the Fleſh; as being moſt riſe amongſt us and ſuch as deſtroy all ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the foulneſs and filthineſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of appears <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1ſt. From the great offence they give to God's own Holineſs and Purity: To which every evil, even in Thought, is oppoſite; Sanctity being his great and moſt proper Attribute, than which the <hi>Seraphims</hi> could find none greater when they ſung, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God of Sabbaoth.</hi> Beſides the Divine Nature being abſolute Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity without any Mixture or Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition whatſoever; and being alſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Perfection, ſo that no defect or want of any good thing is in him; it muſt needs be, that what is contrary to thoſe, as is all imperfection and evilneſs,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53294:13"/>
muſt alſo be oppoſite to him: Which ſpeaking according to the manner of men, is to be diſpleaſing, to be grievous, to be loathſome and odious to him; but moſt of all theſe groſſer ſins.</p>
               <p>And this we know alſo from God's putting all along in Scripture a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar mark of his diſpleaſure upon them; ſetting them in the front as the Captains and Ring-leaders of the reſt. Theſe are the members we are to mortify upon Earth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Affection, evil Concupiſcence, &amp;c.</hi> So again: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9. <hi>be not deceived neither Fornicators,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>nor Adulterers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1 24, <hi>&amp;c. Theſſ.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.1.</note> 
                  <hi>nor Effeminate Perſons, nor Abuſers of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with Mankind,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> Theſe are the ſins with which the <hi>Gentiles</hi> when they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended God moſt of all, before the light of the Goſpel ſhone amongſt them, ſtand every where in Scripture principally charged. Nay ſo great an offence are theſe ſins to the Holineſs of Almighty
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53294:13"/>
God that he ſeems to equal them to the greateſt ſin of all.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5.</note> And therefore in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Write, we find them or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily linked together with the ſin of Idolatry: And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times alſo with Covetouſneſs, taken in its largeſt ſence for Coveting either Perſons or Riches, which laſt is ſaid alſo to be Idolatry: And the former may be called ſo too for the ſame reaſon, becauſe it is hard to ſay which of the two, <hi>Harlots</hi> or <hi>Money,</hi> is moſt powerful and moſt idolized in this lower World.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The Impurity and filthineſs of Fornication and other groſſer ſins of the Fleſh appears yet farther from their oppoſiteneſs to that Holineſs and Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which ought to be in the Body, as well as in the Soul, of all thoſe who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs themſelves Members of Chriſt. Not that this filthineſs of the Fleſh is any Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Deformity in the Body, or any Diſeaſes, Ulcers or Sores: For we find <hi>Job, Lazarus,</hi> and many other great Saints who had been well pleaſing in <hi>God</hi>'s ſight, were before men very loathſom Perſons.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53294:14"/>
But it is a real defilement of the Body, as the Body is the honourable Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Aſſociate of the Soul, and ought by it to be employed to a more noble end, even together with the Soul to be employed to the Glorifying God, and one day alſo to be preſented with it before him in his Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tabernacle.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.4.</note> 
                  <hi>This is the will of God</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul) even your Sanctification, that you ſhould abſtain from Fornication, that every one of you ſhould know how to poſſeſs his Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel</hi> (i. e. his body) <hi>in Sanctification and Honour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>not in Luſt of Concupiſcence, for God hath called us not to uncleanneſs, but unto holineſs.</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle in his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20.</note> addreſſes himſelf to the Men of this Age, as well as thoſe of all others, after a moſt prevailing manner, <hi>Know you not that your body is the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt which is in you, and not your own,</hi> or at your own diſpoſing, <hi>for ye are bought with a price, the precious Blood of our Lord [to be alſo his Spouſe and his Members] therefore ought
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53294:14"/>
to glorifie God both in Body and Soul which are God's.</hi> And is there not good reaſon that after being purchaſed (even our body as well as ſoul) at ſo dear a rate as the Ineſtimable Blood of our Lord, we ſhould at leaſt in gratitude ſanctifie and devote our ſelves wholly to his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſervice? But to compell us to it, unleſs we will deny our ſelves to be Men and rational Creatures, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle's Argument here and in his other Epiſtles, runs thus: <hi>The Church is the Spouſe of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.29, 30, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17.6 13.</note> whom he bought and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed to himſelf with his own Blood and Life, whom he Cheriſheth alſo with the like care as the ſame Fleſh and Bone, and the ſame Spirit with himſelf. And for the ſame reaſon is now our Body as wel as our Soul, for the Lord, and the Lord for the Body. If therefore the Wife have not power over her own Body, but the Husband; no more hath <hi>Chriſt's Spouſe, the Church,</hi> or we her Members,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.34.</note> power over our ſelves, but Chriſt. And tho' it be ſaid only of Virgins that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53294:15"/>
they more eſpecially care for the things of the Lord, how to pleaſe him in every thing, and ſo become Holy both in Body and in Spirit; yet are Married People alſo, as the Circumſtances of their Stations will permit, obliged to care for the things of the Lord above all other things; for the Spouſe of Chriſt, the Church, being a chaſt Virgin (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls her) we that profeſs ourſelves Members of that ſpotleſs Church,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2.</note> whether we be married or unmarried, ought alſo to be chaſt, and neither in action or thought make the Members of Chriſt the members of an Harlot.</p>
               <p>The ſame Apoſtle in his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> Argues ſtill more againſt Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Fly Fornication</hi> (ſaith he) and why ſo? <hi>For every other Sin that a Man doth is without the Body, i. e.</hi> doth not ſo immediately touch the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with any proper Infamy or ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely remove it from under the power of our Lord: But he that committeth Fornication (and much more if Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53294:15"/>
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) ſinneth againſt his own body, <hi>i. e.</hi> diſhonours it the moſt he can by degrading himſelf to ſo baſe an Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance as to become one and the ſame with that vile naſty Creature with whom he ſinneth, and ſo from a pure Member of Chriſt, he renders him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the filthy Member of an Infamous Harlot, or ſomething worſe. I here add that this ſin offers alſo the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Indignity to the Incarnation of the Son of God imaginable, who did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take upon him our Fleſh to exalt it into his own nature (his Heavenly I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage) that no ſuch filthineſs might any longer inhabit in it. To prevent which vileneſs in us, the ſame Apoſtle alſo peculiarly concerning this ſin, or any filthy Diſcourſe tending towards it, gives charge that it ſhould not be ſo much as named amongſt ſuch as would paſs for Chriſtians. <hi>But Fornication</hi> (ſaith he to the <hi>Epheſians) and all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.3, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. let it not be ſo much as once named amongſt you as becometh Saints. Nor Filthineſs, nor Fooliſh Talking, nor Jeſting, which are not Convenient:</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:53294:16"/>
And the Apoſtle there aſſures us that no <hi>Whoremonger or unclean Perſon hath any Inheritance in the Kingdom of Chriſt and of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, the Seal of the Covenant of Grace with <hi>Abraham,</hi> was it not order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God to be ſo particularly placed upon all the Faithful as to become in a manner a puniſhment of their Luſts? And is there not a Natural ſhame upon every man in the committing of thoſe ſins, or any thing like them tho' lawful? So as that the light of the Sun, the ſight of a pious Picture, the coming in of a little Child, or almoſt any of God's Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, even a pious thought (which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds alſo from God) is ſufficient ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to overawe, prevent, and put by, the moſt hardned Sinner from embracing the Temptation. And is it not a burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhame that the preſence of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God and His. Holy Angels, who (with perfect hatred of all Impurities) are continually looking upon us and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading us to the contrary, ſhould not be much more prevalent with us againſt ſuch enormous wickedneſs? But yet
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53294:16"/>
ſo ſtrong are the habits of ſuch Sins as in a manner to diſpoil us of all ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facedneſs, and wholly to alter and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the Nature and Reaſon of thoſe Perſons in which they are; inſomuch that the Practiſers but of one Species of them are called in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations</hi> by the name of <hi>Dogs;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.2.</note> and ſo are the <hi>Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks</hi> by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> for their being guilty of ſome ſuch like impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: As if the Cuſtom and Beaſtlineſs of ſuch ſins did utterly depoſe men from their manhood and change them into Dogs.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, not to omit the greateſt Argument of all of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity and Filthineſs of the ſins of the Fleſh,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16.</note> we find in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> when God had abandoned thoſe Heathens that had firſt forſaken him to follow their own Imaginations (ſince they would not hearken to his Commands which were Holy, Juſt, and Good) they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſuch monſtrous, unnatural Luſts that were the greateſt diſgrace to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53294:17"/>
Nature that poſſibly could be: Men with Men, and ſo Women alſo, committing thoſe things that were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly and unbefitting rational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. God grant that we be not ſo left to our ſelves, ſo given over to our own hearts Luſts, a certain ſign of God's higheſt diſpleaſure, and a fore-runner of his heavieſt Judgments!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53294:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the <hi>puniſhments</hi> of ſuch Sins.</head>
               <p>TO thoſe diſſolute, unthinking Wretches, who will not by the preceeding Arguments be prevailed on to leave their lewd, unmanly Courſe of Life, I ſhall propoſe, in the ſecond place, the <hi>Terrors</hi> of the Lord to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them, the ſevere Puniſhments which inevitably attend ſuch ſins, that the Practiſers thereof may moſt rightly meaſure the greatneſs of their faults (which they make Natural, and for that reaſon excuſable,) by the great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge God himſelf takes of them. Thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> warns his <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians</hi> to abſtain from the <hi>Fornication of the Gentiles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>the defrauding our Brother of his Wife,</hi> &amp;c And what is the reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, <hi>the Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is the avenger of all ſuch,</hi> all manner of Luſts, even
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53294:18"/>
thoſe commited only in the heart. And ſo in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> he pronounceth the ſame thing,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Marriage is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and the bed undefiled, but Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers and Adulterers God will Judge.</hi> And in deteſtation of ſuch unlawful Luſts, the Lord appointed under <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law, <hi>That a Baſtard ſhould not enter into the Congregation of the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.2.</note> 
                  <hi>until the tenth Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</hi> And does not the Prophet <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah</hi> moſt particularly threaten in God's Name ſuch Sinners for their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling in Troops into Harlots Houſes, and running like fed Horſes after their Neighbours Wives, <hi>Shall I not Viſit for theſe things</hi> (ſaith the Lord),<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſhall not my Soul be avenged of ſuch a Nation as this?</hi> Thoſe Expreſſions, <hi>The Lord is the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venger, God will Judge, the Lord appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhall I not viſit,</hi> plainly ſhow that God taketh the puniſhing all ſuch abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations into his own hands, that they may be ſure not to go unpuniſhed even in this Life.</p>
               <p>But this is not all, we find in Sacred
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53294:18"/>
Scripture God inflicting on theſe ſins not ordinary puniſhments, but ſuch fearful Judgments to which none other can be compared. The drowning of the whole World (about a Thouſand Years after its Creation, when all Fleſh, excepting ſome very few Perſons, had corrupted their ways) was it not to waſh away its pollution from theſe ſins with a Flood? And how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſand Souls better than our ſelves periſhed in that Deluge? The dreadful Raining of Fire and Brimſtone from Heaven upon thoſe miſerable brutiſh Cities, <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha,</hi> and the Cities about them (which yet perhaps were not ſo bad as ſome Cities even now-a-days amongſt us) was it not to purifie their Land (which was once a Paradiſe upon Earth) from thoſe loathſome ſins by Fire? The driving out all thoſe mighty Nations from <hi>Canaan,</hi> and deſtroying them, and giving their Land to the Children of <hi>Iſrael for a poſſeſſion,</hi> was it not for theſe abominable ſins? See the eightenth Chapter of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viticus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lev.</hi> 18.</note> whereafter variety
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53294:19"/>
of thoſe ſins rehearſed (ſuch as are not fit to be named amongſt Chriſtians but with horror and deteſtation of them) it follows, <hi>Verſe.</hi> 27. <hi>For all theſe abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations</hi> (the Name God himſelf there gives to theſe loathſome ſins) <hi>have the Men of the Land done before you and the Land is defiled;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the Verſe following, this defiled Land is ſaid to have <hi>ſpewed</hi> out the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants thereof who defiled it. In like manner the Deſtruction of the <hi>Shechemites,</hi> the Death of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> the Judgment of God upon the Three and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thouſand of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.8.</note> who fell in one Day at <hi>Baal-Peor,</hi> before they entered <hi>Canaan,</hi> were they not for ſuch Sins as theſe? And for the like Sins (even for one lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urious, adulterous Act) was not the whole Tribe of <hi>Benjamin</hi> cut off,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Judg.</hi> 20.</note> except only Six hundred Men? I might here add the remarkable Wars and Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that ſuddenly followed upon <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s Adultery: as alſo the rending of the ten Tribes from <hi>Solomon,</hi> as a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53294:19"/>
Judgment for his being ſeduced to the Toleration of Idolatry, by his exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Luſts and unlawful Marriages; and many more the like ſad Examples, even out of the Annals of our own and other neighbouring Countries. And here alſo I might ſet down more at large God's particular Denunciations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch Sins, by the Mouth of all his Prophets; ſometimes inflicting his great Judgments, <hi>Plague, Peſtilence, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, Sword,</hi> removing his Candleſticks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But I think what is already ſaid is enough to ſhew that theſe Sins of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, tho ſeeming moſt excuſable, and natural to Man, are moſt abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and loathſom in the ſight of God: Eſpecially, ſince by the new Contract that is made between us and our Lord, we are become in a more peculiar manner,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.</note> the Spouſe of Chriſt; and are therefore to keep our ſelves Chaſt and Holy: We are become likewiſe by a particular and higher de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Sanctification, the <hi>Temples of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19.</note> and are therefore not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegiouſly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53294:20"/>
to violate 'em, <hi>but to cleanſe them from all Filthineſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo perfecting that Holineſs which becomes God's Houſe for ever:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 92.5.</note> And this at our utmoſt Peril, <hi>For theſe Temples</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul) whoſo defileth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17.</note> 
                  <hi>him will God eternally deſtroy.</hi> And a great Moraliſt that lived at the ſame time with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> (and probably alſo was made a Chriſtian by him, with ſome others of <hi>Nero</hi>'s Houſhold) ſays in a manner the ſame thing (according to <hi>Lactantius, De Div. Inſtit. Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>C.</hi> 25.) <hi>The moſt agreeable Temple we can build for God, is to conſecrate him in our Hearts:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to build otherwiſe would be to ruin our ſelves to all Eternity, which tranſcendently exceeds all temporal Puniſhments put together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:53294:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Chaſtity of Marriage, and the Purity of a ſingle Life.</head>
               <p>THus far concerning, <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Impurity and Filthineſs of the Sins of the Fleſh, with their Oppoſiteneſs to the Purity and Holineſs of Almighty God, and the defilement and diſhonour they bring to the Perſons that commit them: And, <hi>Secondly,</hi> the ſevere Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments and tremendous Judgments of Almighty God towards ſuch Sins above others.</p>
               <p>But, I would not, by any means, be thought ſo to have cenſured in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this Diſcourſe, the preſent Age, as if there were not many amongſt the married Perſons, whom God hath reſerved to himſelf (even in our own Nation) moſt inviolably conſtant to one another, and that live ſtrictly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Bounds and Obligations of that honourable State: And ſome alſo of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53294:21"/>
the Unmarried, that live ſingle out of Choice, not Neceſſity; upon the account of Vertue and Religion, not Licentiouſneſs and Luxury: And many alſo, who after one Marriage, abſtain from a Second, upon the ſame ſerious account; as did thoſe Widows in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.</note> who were for that very reaſon taken into the Charity and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Church.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>MARRIAGE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Marriage is Honourable in all and the Bed undefiled with ſin:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. v. <hi>32.</hi>
                     </note> So Honourable that St. <hi>Paul</hi> compares the Union of Man and Wife with that of Chriſt and his Church: But yet doubtleſs conjugal Chaſtity hath many Degrees in it, and in ſome is far more pure than in others. More pure in thoſe who for better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of Holy Duties; or in Times of Humiliation, ſuch as <hi>Lent, Ember-Weeks, &amp;c. before receiving the Bleſſed Sacrament,</hi> and the like, abſtain and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate, that they may give themſelves to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53294:21"/>
Faſting and Prayer. So in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.15 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.4.</note> before the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent <hi>of the Lord</hi> upon <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> the People were commanded <hi>three days Sanctification, and not coming at their Wives.</hi> Women kept from the Young Men for about <hi>three days,</hi> and the Veſſels of the <hi>Young Men Holy [i. e.</hi> from their Wives.] And in times of more earneſt Addreſſes to God, this ſeparation from Carnality was continually uſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from the Prophet <hi>Zechary.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zech.</hi> 7.3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But Conjugal Chaſtity is ſtill more pure in thoſe, who being ſeparated for a longer time, either upon the account of Sickneſs in one Party, or by neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry abſence of either of them about Worldly Affairs, in Journeys, Publick Employments, Embaſſies, or being taken Captive by an Enemy and the like, yet both continue conſtant and faithful to one another, and this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps for many years, notwithſtanding the many ſtrong Temptations the world preſents.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:53294:22"/>So in the Caſe of Divorcement, or of a reſolved Separation by conſent, many there are who take from hence an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of being more diligent in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, and afterwards perhaps of removing themſelves out of all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being enſnared and ruined by the Sollicitations of Senſe. And ſo likewiſe after Eſpouſals, ſome there have been, tho' not many, who according to the Tranſcendent Example of our Bleſſed Lady and her Eſpouſed Husband St. <hi>Joſeph,</hi> have never proceeded any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but inſtead of Conſummating the Marriage, have transferred their Love and Affection to our Lord. So St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> treated with his Spouſe, and after having once vanquiſhed himſelf and his exorbitantly Incontinent Deſires (of which himſelf ſo much complains, and in his Confeſſions Laments) ſo as to be content even without Marriage it ſelf, became a moſt Holy Biſhop, and one of the moſt Glorious Lights in the Church of God that ever the World ſaw ſince the times of our Saviour and his Apoſtles. And in our own Nation King <hi>Edward</hi> (commonly called the Saint) lived to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53294:22"/>
with his Queen a holy Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Life, as <hi>Surius</hi> ſhews out of a very Ancient Manuſcript. As did alſo <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt Emperour, <hi>Boliſlaus</hi> (the modeſt) King of <hi>Poland, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> II King of <hi>Caſtile, Peter <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rceoli</hi> Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> with may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his 45 E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle encourageth a chaſte Married Couple to perſiſt unalterably in their Holy Intention of abſtaining, by urg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them ſome great Examples, and telling them that Wedlock may ſtill be maintained without Carnality, by preſerving entire the affection of the mind.</p>
                  <p>Since then thoſe Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages are to be Eſteemed moſt Chaſt which come neareſt to a <hi>Single Life,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Single Life.</note> and allow moſt time for Devotion; and ſince alſo there are none in a Married State ſo pure as to propoſe nothing elſe by Marriage, but the having of Children and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them up in the fear of God and ſo filling Heaven with immortal Souls,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53294:23"/>
without any mixture of groſs ſenſual Pleaſure and Carnal Satisfaction to themſelves; and that many times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bounds fixed and allowed by almighty God, who ordained Man and Wife to be helps to one another chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſpirituals; it muſt be granted in favour of thoſe few (few Compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively ſpeaking) who in Colleges, Inns-of-Court and the like, make choice of a <hi>Single Life,</hi> that ſuch a manner of Life (when truly Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous) hath the Preheminence of the Married State (ordinarily ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) even in its greateſt purity.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For 1ſt. though the Married-bed be undefiled <hi>i. e.</hi> with ſin, yet is the Virgins Bed more undefiled, more <hi>Angel-like</hi> in reſpect of Corporeal purity.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.35.</note> And therefore hereafter not to Marry, <hi>nor be given in Marriage, but to be like the Angels of God,</hi> is reckoned as a thing more Honourable for the body. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence indeed hath a ſhare in the <hi>Single Life</hi> as well as in the Married:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53294:23"/>
But before the fall there was no ſuch thing in humane Nature as Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence; and ſince the fall it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the <hi>Single Life</hi> aims at a higher Degree of that <hi>Primogeneral. Virginal</hi> purity that was in Man in the State of Innocency: What elſe can be the meaning of that Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.34.</note> 
                     <hi>The Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin careth, &amp;c. that ſhe may be holy both in Body and Spirit? Holy,</hi> that is certainly more holy and more pure than ſhe could have been in a Married ſtate.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2ly. The <hi>Single Life</hi> is free<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> from Diſtractions, Worldly Cares and Impediments than the Married Life can be. When a Man hath double Obligations relating to this World, and the next, and both of them require the greateſt part of his time, he is as it were divided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two, and knows not which to attend to firſt, or how to quit his Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to one without incurring the diſpleaſure of the other. Whereas
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53294:24"/>
if a Man have his Liberty (which when we can have we are rather to uſe it 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.21.) and is not entangled with the preſent World, hath no Wife or Family and none to take care of but himſelf, what can hinder him from Dedicating himſelf, his time and all that he can do or ſuffer to the Glory and Service of God? I would have you (ſaith the Holy Spirit by St. <hi>Paul</hi> to his <hi>Corinthians</hi>) be [as much as may be] without carefulneſs;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Bor.</hi> 7.32.</note> eſpecially the Paſtors and Watchmen of Gods Church, who are to give an account of the Souls committed to their charge.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</note> And it follows in the ſame Verſe, <hi>He that is unmarried careth for the things of the Lord, how he may pleaſe the Lord; but he that is Married careth for the things of the Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ld, how he may pleaſe his Wife, and ſo ſhe that is Married how ſhe may pleaſe her Husband:</hi> And yet the Married (both Men and Women)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53294:24"/>
muſt endeavour alſo to pleaſe the Lord (who hath an abſolute power over them precedent to all others) and ſo are divided in their thoughts and cannot attend upon the Lord [in Prayer and other holy Duties] with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great diſtraction and ſolicitude. For indeed nothing can be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Spiritual Exerciſes (ſuch as Prayer, Faſting and the like) than Carnal Pleaſures; which by the very Exceſſes they feed upon, and are therewith kept alive, diſcompoſe our Temper, and divide and divert our Love and Affections to the Creature, which are always beſt ſpent upon and conſecrated to the Creator himſelf.</p>
                  <p>The Prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi> who was the firſt that ſet up the Standard of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity upon <hi>Mount Carmel,</hi> was alſo himſelf a true Emblem of it, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Fire and Zeal for the ſervice of God, Propheſying and Preaching the Truth boldly, even at Court, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having any regard either to world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intereſt or his own ſafety: And
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53294:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
therefore after a Pure, Virginal, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Life here, God Tranſlated him by an extraordinary manner that he ſhould not ſee Death.<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.22, 24.</note> Which indeed happened alſo to <hi>Enoch</hi> a Married Perſon, for his walking with God and giving a good Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in thoſe early days of Religion, before the World was come to ſuch perfection as to know the Excellency of Virginity and the Single Life; and beſides that good Patriarchs Family being then perhaps the only Church of God, he might juſtly think the encreaſing of it to be then of abſolute neceſſity: Eſpecially ſince even in our times there are not wanting ſome Eminent Perſons, who Marry for no other end than to raiſe up Godly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies that ſhall imitate themſelves in Piety and Devotion, and in walking like <hi>Enoch</hi> with God. Which never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, tho' it be the moſt perfect Scope of Marriage, yet comes not up to the Purity and Perfection of Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53294:25"/>
and the Single Life, that is always ſitting at the feet of Jeſus, and inceſſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attending on the ſervice of God.</p>
                  <p>It is upon this very account that St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his comparing theſe two States together in his 1ſt. Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.38.</note> gives the preference to a ſingle Life before Marriage. <hi>He that giveth her in Marriage doth well, but he that giveth her not in Marriage doth bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> And ſo of a Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 40.</note> the ſame Apoſtle pronounceth her happier in his Judgment if ſhe ſo abide. Better and happier then is the Single Life to thoſe that can live con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently (and who ever uſed the means of Faſting, Prayer, frequent Communicating, avoiding Occaſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with ſincerity and failed?) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch being freed from Worldly cares, which occaſion diſtractions, their Affections and Underſtanding are better diſpoſed for meditating and contemplating on Divine things, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53294:26"/>
for receiving more and more Gifts and Graces of the Holy Spirit, and ſo may be ſaid to live more ſenſible of the Preſence as well as the Bleſſing of Almighty God, which is the only happineſs (in this vale of miſeries) of humane life. And ſuch Single Perſons as are of meaner Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and ſo not capable of theſe higher matters, have yet by living Single more leiſure for Works of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity towards their Neighbour, which are altogether as acceptable to God, but yet not without the other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Duties even of the moſt ignorant Chriſtians, ſuch as daily Prayers, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting the Bleſſed Sacrament, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Paſtours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ought not to be omitted upon any even pious Pretence whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>The Encomiums of a Single Life are endleſs. St. <hi>Paul</hi> recommends it to all Chriſtians (much more than to the higheſt rank of them)<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.32, 35.</note> before the pleaſures of Marriage
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53294:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
(to avoid the great Carefulneſs and Diſtractions that neceſſarily attend that State:) Even to thoſe alſo that after enjoyment have left their Wives (<hi>i. e.</hi> by mutual conſent) upon the ſame Spiritual account. And when our Saviour ſaith, <hi>There be ſome who have made themſelves Eunuchs</hi> (by embracing a Single Life) <hi>for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heavens ſake, [i. e.</hi> For the better ſerving God in any way.] <hi>He who is able to receive it, let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it,</hi> what is it but a Recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to his followers (particularly to his Diſciples and Guides of his Church) of that happier Condition? And as to that popular pretence of multiplying the World and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Succeſſion of Generations, that is not the care of Man but of God; and Individual Perſons (as many as are ſo reſolved in their minds) may ſafely chuſe the better State in order to their own greater happineſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fearing the ruine of the World to enſue. And indeed our Saviour (the fountain of all Purity) by that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53294:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Expreſſion <hi>of making themſelves Eunuchs,</hi> ſeems to grant (as St. <hi>Cryſoſtome</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) the power of living a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Single Life, a life of <hi>Eunuchiſm,</hi> to all ſincere endeavourers. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo when he reckons up to his <hi>Corinthians,</hi> his own good Actions and Labours,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.6.</note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts amongſt them <hi>Pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> or <hi>Chaſtity;</hi> which he would not have done if he had thought it the mere Gift of God without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence or acquiſition of his own Watchings and Faſtings and Prayers. If then thoſe Married Perſons are commended and promiſed a Reward who keep themſelves within the bounds of Marriage, chaſt from Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, Uncleanneſs, and all unlawful Carnal Pleaſures; and thoſe alſo a higher Reward who Renounce the pleaſures of Marriage and leave their Wives (conſenting thereunto) for the Kingdom of Heavens ſake, that they may love God the more entirely <hi>with all their Heart, all their Soul and all their Strength,</hi> (which is the great
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53294:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Commandment of all); what ſhall be done with thoſe Virgins that have with much pains and difficulty ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained, not only from unlawful, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Pleaſures, <hi>Fornication, &amp;c.</hi> but alſo from the lawful, thoſe of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage? It is certainly more Heroical (as a Holy Man obſerves) with Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins wholly to repell the importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Fleſh, than with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried only lawfully to ſatisfie them: A greater vertue to ſubdue, than only to moderate the moſt Violent of our Paſſions. Their reward therefore in Heaven muſt be proportionably greater, anſwerable to the ſeveral greater Degrees of Purity to which they have here attained. Of them it is ſaid in the <hi>Revelations</hi> (at leaſt of thoſe of the higheſt degree of Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Purity) <hi>Theſe are they who were not defiled with Women,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.4.</note> 
                     <hi>for they are Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins:</hi> And they are there alſo called, <hi>The firſt Fruits unto God, and unto the Lamb:</hi> And their Tranſcendent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is, <hi>They follow the Lamb whether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53294:28"/>
he goeth.</hi> And of whom elſe is it ſaid, but of the moſt pure Virgin-Mother of our Lord, <hi>That all Generations ſhall call her Bleſſed.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 1.48.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>If it ſhould here be objected, That in this Diſcourſe there is little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſaid concerning the ſins of the Fleſh being alſo contrary to the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Soul as well as of the Body; it is anſwered, That ſuch ſins are more directly oppoſite to the purity of the Body, as being committed in it, and cannot be committed without it, and are thence called the ſins of the Fleſh: Care therefore being taken of the Purity of the Body, the Purity of the Soul is included as to theſe ſins. Not but there are other ſins called Spiritual, more proper to the Soul and more directly oppoſite to its pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and more dangerous alſo, becauſe not ſo eaſily diſcernable by us as are the ſins of the Fleſh, ſuch as Pride, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy, Ambition, Envy, Wrath, Contentions of Argument, Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53294:28"/>
to Superiours, Rebellion, Witchcraft, Curioſity of Science, Schiſm, Hereſy, and the like, which together with their chief Remedies, Humility, Lowlineſs of Mind, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Judgment, Contentedneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> would be ſufficient matter for ſo many different Diſcourſes. And I might here inſert how far an obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Blindneſs, Ignorance or Errour in the Underſtanding, and a Peeviſh Perverſneſs in the Will, may be ſaid to be the chief, if not the only, Cauſes of theſe ſubtiler and more Spiritual wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſes of the Soul. But at preſent it ſhall ſuffice to have given ſome ſhort account of the abominable ſins of the Fleſh, and the ſad Conſequences there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; Superadding only (which I could not omit) what is ſo particularly markt out to us by St. <hi>Jude</hi> concerning Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:<note place="margin">Jud. v. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </note> The Heads and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers of which, he calls, <hi>Filthy Dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that defile the Fleſh, deſpiſe Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſpeak evil of Dignities.</hi> This Character is ſo plain that I need not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53294:29"/>
point out the Perſons concerned in it. For who are theſe <hi>Filthy Dreamers,</hi> but thoſe who pretend Revelations and Illuminations from God to ſerve their own Luſts, who forſaking the Guides and Governours God hath ſet over them; and ſetting up for their own Paſſions, either of Revenge, or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, or Ambition and the like; and finding no encouragement either in God's Word or from good Men for what they do, perhaps do perſwade themſelves, at leaſt pretend to others, that they have new Advices, new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, new Lights from Heaven: And vainly puffed up in their Fleſhly mind, do think to ſhelter themſelves and their wickedneſs under a pretext, under the Fige leaves of Godlineſs and Spirituality; till like <hi>Corah</hi> and his Company <hi>Dreaming themſelves holy,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Num.</hi> 16.31</note> and offering to God falſe Fire, they are ſuddenly ſwallowed up, even before they can awake out of their filthy Dream.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:53294:29"/>I proceed next to the Cure and Prevention of the Sins of the Fleſh, by obſerving to the ſerious Reader, ſome few uſeful Rules out of thoſe many, Preſcribed by Pious and Learned Men for the direction of themſelves and others.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:53294:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>The firſt Rule,</hi> Of our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, Memory <hi>and</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> FIrſt we muſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to know our own Paſſions and Inclinations, which if not rightly Governed, do in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner biaſs the Soul to what they pleaſe, and are for that reaſon narrowly to be watcht; eſpecially the Paſſion of Love, as being the very Source of all the reſt. For if our Love and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be once fixed and chained to any one object, it grows then unruly: All other Paſſions and Reaſon it ſelf muſt give way to it. <hi>Its Bands are ſtrong,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtrong as death,</hi> ſaith the Spouſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:53294:30"/>
in the <hi>Canticles;</hi> Death that ſwallows all. All our Faculties and Powers become Vaſſals to this Paſſion (even our fears often proceed from our too great love), it hurries them on and when not rightly placed, it never ſtops but in our ruine: Forcing us many times againſt our minds <hi>(video melio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra proboque, deteriora, &amp;c.)</hi> to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs our duty to God and our ſelves, to lay aſide our Liberty and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood together, and become Dogs, Swine, abſolute Slaves to our Luſts, and ſo wholly defacing the glorious Image of God engraven in us, transforms us into Veſſels of Diſhonour fitted and prepared by our own folly for Eternal Deſtruction. The Young Man that is deceived and enticed by a Whore (who invites him in with a <hi>Stolen Waters are ſweet, Bread eaten in a corner is pleaſant,</hi> or ſome ſuch little Inveigl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Devices of the Devil;) follows her (ſays the Wiſeman) <hi>As an Ox goeth to the Slaughter (i. e.</hi> with Greedineſs, as thinking he is going to a freſh Paſture;) <hi>and as a Fool to the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:53294:31"/>
of the Stocks,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any foreſight at all;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov</hi> 5.5.9.18.</note> not knowing that he is in any danger <hi>till a Dart ſtrike thro his Liver. Where as her houſe is the ready way to the Grave, going down to the Chambers of Death, and her ſteps layhold on Hell.</hi> Behold the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful end of a ſinful diſhonourable Love: Which well conſidered is certainly the beſt Remedy to ſtop the Fooliſh beginnings thereof: And to cauſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to fly to their Veil to ſecure their Beauty from occaſioning their ruine, and to take Adulteries out of their boſom and beware of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity which is always Criminal. But then on the contrary if this powerful Paſſion of Love be rightly managed, ſo as to be once fixed upon its true object, Almighty God, and to hate for love of him all ſin, and with St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>count all things loſs and dung to gain Chriſt;</hi> it then ſurmounts all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties and caſts out all fears, and renders the whole duty of a Chriſtian
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53294:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
eaſie, and Sufferings and Perſecutions for Chriſts ſake deſirable, that he may thereby more pleaſe God and become more conformable to our Lord, of which more afterwards.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Our Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Imagination are to be mortified. We muſt not ſuffer our ſelves to ruminate and feed our Fancies upon paſt ſenſual Pleaſures (our own or other Mens;) for that is next to our Acting them over again. Thus the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when they were deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God himſelf from the midſt of a ſinful Nation, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly fed <hi>in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs with Manna from Heaven,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Num.</hi> 11.5, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>longed and luſted after the Fleſh-pots of Egypt,</hi> and ſo diſpleaſed Almighty God more by wiſhing for them again than when they actually enjoyed them. So St. <hi>Peter</hi> Compares a Chriſtians return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Filthineſs, from which he hath once eſcaped,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22</note> 
                  <hi>to a Dogs
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53294:32"/>
returning to his vomit, and a Swine that is clean to her wallowing in the mire.</hi> And our Saviour himſelf hath particularly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned us.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.62.</note> 
                  <hi>That whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever hath put his hand to the Plough</hi> [i. e. profeſſed himſelf a Chriſtian] <hi>looking back</hi> [with any delight to his former ſinful courſe of life] <hi>is not fit for the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> We are therefore moſt carefully to mind theſe two Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, eſpecially conſidering they are the very Store-houſe of the Soul: (See St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his Confeſſions (<hi>lib.</hi> 10.8.) concerning the boundleſs Capaciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Memory for the compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the Images of all things that can any way fall under Mans Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration:) Which therefore if filled with filthy Idea's, obſcene Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the like, moſt of all diſturb and diſtract us, and are the greateſt hinderance to Piety imaginable; and indeed the main Engine by which the Devil works (according to the power now left him) his malicious deſigns upon us. Whereas on the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53294:32"/>
contrary if they be filled with good Objects, devout Repreſentations, they do unavoidably cauſe great Piety and Devotion in us, and our hearts can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be ſet upon ſuch Rich, Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Treaſure: Becauſe our Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alone hath ſo great influence upon us either to good or bad, that ſuch as our Fancy is, ſuch is our Love, and ſuch is the whole Man. Every one is drawn <hi>(trahit ſua quemque, &amp;c.)</hi> by ſome forcible Fancy, ſomething that pleaſes, and according as that is thereafter are our thoughts: It is well therefore if that <hi>ſomething</hi> be either Truth or Juſtice, or Beatitude and Eternal Life, the only true End and Scope of a Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>Now in our watchfulneſs over theſe two faculties we are to have a particular Eye,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1ſt. to <hi>Our outward Senſes.</hi> Not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering them to approach, at leaſt not dwell upon, ſinful Objects; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving them preſently from us or us from them. For not Arguing
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53294:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
with, but rather running away from them is the ſureſt Remedy againſt the Temptations of all ſenſual Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; it being much eaſier to keep our ſelves from any knowledge or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of them, than after experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encing them (ſo great is the Pravity of our Nature) from longing after them, eſpecially thoſe which are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citements to Luſt. <hi>A Whoriſh Woman</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) will hunt for the precious Life of a Man;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.26, 27.</note> and you may as ſafely take fire into your boſome, or walk upon hot bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Coals as Converſe with her, or even look upon her without having firſt made a Covenant with your Eyes.</p>
               <p>When therefore our Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are ſuch that we cannot well avoid the preſence of a Tempting Object, our beſt Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient is,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2ly. To retire immediately into our ſelves to Diſcourſe with God (who
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53294:33"/>
ſtands always knocking ready to be admitted and to enter with us into our Soul) and particularly to pray and beſeech him either to remove the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Temptation or preſerve us from it.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.20.</note> Or (the ſooner to put it out of our mind) we may recite any Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionatly pious Devotions or <hi>Pſalms,</hi> we have ready ſtored up in our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, which will make our Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (not capable of long minding two things at once) unawares quit its former ſinful object. Or we may conſider with our ſelves the bitterneſs and ſting ſin (whatſoever) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted leaves behind it, by reaſon of the uncertainty of our true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Sincere Reformation of Life. Or we may meditate on the Dolorous Paſſion of our Saviour which rent the very Rocks;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6.</note> or any part of his ſufferings in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, at the Pillar, upon the Croſs; and that Voluntarily to ſin is as much as in us lies to Crucify him afreſh. Or
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53294:34"/>
on ſome one of the Four laſt things. On <hi>Death,</hi> which puts an end to all Earthly pleaſures in a moment, and ſeparates a wicked Soul not only from the Body, but from God forever. On the <hi>laſt Judgment,</hi> when the dreadful Sentence on Drolling Debauchees and all Impenitents will be, <hi>Go ye Curſed.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41</note> On <hi>Hell,</hi> That everlaſting Fire whither the Curſed are to go. Or laſtly, <hi>On the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſpeakable Joys of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> which may be ſo advantageouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repreſented to the Soul as to drive out the thoughts of all other pleaſures. For there the Bleſſed have their Knowledge perfected,<note place="margin">Pſ. 63.5.</note> their Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons rewarded more than they were in the leaſt worthy.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.18</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 22.4.4.8.</note> They poſſeſs all Riches, all Honour, enjoy all Pleaſures, are raviſhed with the Beauty and Holineſs of our Lord;<note place="margin">Eph. 4.10.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 17.21, 23.</note> filled with the fulnes of God, made
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:53294:34"/>
one with Chriſt and with God: Which are thoſe high things ſo far ſurpaſſing our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding that (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to St. <hi>Paul) Eye hath not ſeen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9. 2 Cor. 12.4.</note> 
                  <hi>nor Ear heard, nor hath it ever entred into the heart of Man to conceive them.</hi> And if none or all of theſe Meditations and innumerable others relating to our Saviour and another World (with which the Holy Scriptures and other good Books amply ſupply us) cannot prevail to ſecure us, it is certainly much better rudely to quit the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and leap out of the flames, than to ſtay out of Complaiſance to be burnt in them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:53294:35"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>The Second</hi> Rule, <hi>Of</hi> Suggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</head>
               <p>THE Second Inſtruction is, To take great care of Suggeſtions, and to obſerve from what Principle or Cauſe they proceed: Whether, 1ſt. From our ſelves, or our own Luſts; Or, 2ly. From the Devil; Or, 3ly. From the H. Spirit of God; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly we are either to entertain or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject them. Now it is not eaſie, even for the greateſt <hi>Aſceticks</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern upon all occaſions from which of theſe Principles a Suggeſtion ariſes; but if it be ſuch as tempteth us to any Notorious ſin, any Filthy unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, we may preſently know from whence it comes. And then it is much better and eaſier to ſuppreſs it in its very beginning, to ſtifle it in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53294:35"/>
the <hi>Embryo</hi> before it be conceived in us by our conſenting to it, or at leaſt before it break forth into any outward action, which <hi>when finiſhed brings forth Death.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.15.</note> Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, unclean Suggeſtions we cannot always prevent, but we may refuſe conſenting to them, or taking any delight in them; and ſo ſuppreſs and keep them under (by God's Aſſiſtance) till at length we Totally extinguiſh them. O that God's Holy Spirit would take ſuch full poſſeſſion of my heart as not to ſuffer any unclean Suggeſtion to enter there!</p>
               <p>But if the ſin to which we are temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted be habitual to us, or the <hi>ſin which doth moſt eaſily</hi> of all others <hi>beſet us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1.</note> we are then to bend all our forces againſt it, make the ſtrongeſt reſolutions we can, for ſome ſhort time at leaſt, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for a day, and ſo renew our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions every Morning (the known
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:53294:36"/>
practice of a Renowned Biſhop of the <hi>Church of England</hi> in Point of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony) taking particular Notice how often it aſſaults us, and in the midſt of the Temptation uſing ſome external action (if nothing but vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence will do) ſuch as throwing our ſelves down upon our knees or face, beating our Breaſt, ſupplicating our Lord with ſighs and tears (when God pleaſes to give them) for his aſſiſtance, who hath promiſed that <hi>he will not ſuffer us to be tempted above what we are able,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13.</note> 
                  <hi>but will with the Temptation make a way for our Eſcape,</hi> or enable us to bear the preſſure of it. At leaſt, it is wiſdom to delay the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the foul Act to which we are tempted, for by deferring it, our reaſon may gather new forces, our Paſſions abate; or ſome External Accidents may intervene: Some pious reflection of our own may occurr; or ſome good Friend may come in, to whom we may impart our deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Condition and ask his good
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:53294:36"/>
Advice, who at ſuch a time is much better able than we our ſelves to give it; and in this ſence chiefly it is that the bearing one anothers burdens is the fulfilling of the Law of Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>After the vanquiſhing of ſuch a Temptation, and the leaving as far as we can our own Nature to go o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to Grace, there uſually comes an Angel to comfort us, or what is better, ſome holy Inſpiratons of the Divine Spirit to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline us (who of our ſelves cannot ſo much as think a good thought) to thank God for our delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5.</note> and to pray for more Grace and Strength againſt another time. Such <hi>holy</hi> Inſpirations we muſt take care not to repell; for that would be more or leſs to Reſiſt, Grieve, and Quench the Holy Spirit of God in us: But on the contrary we muſt Cheriſh all good Thoughts, and by them endeavour to introduce, by little and little, Vertues inſtead of our ill Habits. When once
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:53294:37"/>
we intend to begin a new Courſe of Life, we muſt not in the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with Fleſh and Blood, but rather fall immediately upon it. <hi>If at any time, why not now, if not now, perhaps never?</hi> Was the ſaying of St. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> And in the acquiring of any Vertue, ſuppoſe Continency, Chaſtity or the like, we may (with the ſame Father) boldly throw our ſelves upon God who will not withdraw himſelf to let us fall, <hi>Projice te in Deum, &amp;c.</hi> But yet our own ſincere Endeavours after a pure mind and right intention muſt not be wanting, to which God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways gives a Bleſſing tho' we are not always ſenſible of it.</p>
               <p>Now ſome perhaps may think Solemn Reſolutions to one Juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to break a long cuſtom and habit of any filthy ſin to be both Raſh and Dangerous, becauſe when once broken (as many times firſt Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions are, the ill habit being as yet much ſtronger than the good one to be introduced) the over-grown Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:53294:37"/>
is apt to be either too much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged and ſo fall into deſpair; or to be more hardned in his moſt ſhameful Vice, and ſo Incorrigibly go on ſtill in his old wonted Road of Debauchery: It may therefore be much ſafer for a beginner to make a limited Conditional Promiſe and ſuch as is Releaſable upon a Forefeiture. Suppoſe (for Example) we reſolve to abſtain from ſuch a filthy ſin, from ſuch lewd Company, for ſo long a time, or if we do not we will indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſibly pay ſo much Money to be given to the poor, ſay ſo many Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, faſt ſo many Meals, ſhut up our ſelves ſo many Days from all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and the like (and this beſides and over and above the neceſſary requiſites of our Repentance); which preſent forefeiture or puniſhment (in our Purſe or otherwiſe) many times hath a greater Influence upon us towards the breaking off a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched Cuſtom, than either the fears or hopes of what may and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53294:38"/>
will happen to us (according to our deſerts) in another World.</p>
               <p>Moreover, the reſolving upon ſuch a Penalty for the Forefeiture as does really afflict the Body, ſuch as Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, long Retirement, Watching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or diminiſhing our beloved trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure and ſubſtance, by giving large Alms to Priſons, Hoſpitals, poor Houſe-keepers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will certainly fix in our memory an hatred of the ſin, and ſo mind us of every Suggeſtion of it, and deterr us from embracing it: becauſe, if a temporal puniſhment be immediately to follow it much leſſens the deſire of the imaginary pleaſure, and oftentimes occaſions the reflecting alſo on the future real puniſhment, eternal Death, which is the final Doom and the Inſeparable wages of all unrepented,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23.</note> unforſaken ſin. But then to every good purpoſe we muſt not forget to joyn this Reſolution alſo, that if we ſhould at any time by infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, or ſurprize, relapſe into the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable ſin againſt which we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:53294:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
(for <hi>he that ſtands muſt take heed leaſt he falls,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.21.</note> and be not high minded but fear) we will not however abandon our ſelves to it, but on the contrary renew and make ſtronger Reſolutions againſt it with ſeverer Penalties annexed, and ſo valiantly continue on the fight till it ſhall pleaſe God to give us the Victory.</p>
               <p>Such voluntary Mortifications are likewiſe Efficacious not only for the taming and keeping under the body, but for the obtaining alſo from God (by our thus ſiding and taking part with his Divine Juſtice againſt our ſins) the particular Gift and Grace of which we ſtand in need. Some un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Luſt is not to be ſubdued,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.21.</note> ſome Devil not caſt out <hi>without Faſting as well as Prayer.</hi> Our ſparing Self-Mortifications, is like ſparing the Rod to the Child, but the uſing of them is the ready way to prevent God's Judgments from falling upon us in particular; or upon our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53294:39"/>
for our ſakes, and by reaſon of our ſins, or to remove them when begun <hi>Thus</hi> Ezra <hi>and his People faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and beſought God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezra</hi> 8.21.</note> 
                  <hi>and he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated for them.</hi> And ſo another time Queen <hi>Eſther</hi> and the whole <hi>Jewiſh Nation</hi> juſt as they were going to be Maſſacred,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſt.</hi> 4.16.</note> were preſerved by the ſame means of <hi>Faſting and Prayer.</hi> The <hi>Ninevites</hi> alſo were ſpared upon the ſame account of their great Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, <hi>Jon.</hi> 3.10. And ſo the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Daniel</hi> attained to ſo great Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Wiſdom, and ſo high a degree of the Divine Favour, by his long faſting and mourning and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for God's only Church and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; <hi>Dan.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.3. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I know no other way of ſtoping God's Judgments, even when they are breaking out upon us, than by thus applying our ſelves to Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lify his Juſtice that we may not fail of his Mercy.</p>
               <p>But yet the greateſt Humiliation
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:53294:39"/>
of all, and moſt Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.16.</note> 
                  <hi>is the telling our ſins to one another as often as we commit them,</hi> particularly to our Spiritual Paſtors, which will be apt to awe us (if not hardned) from ſinning in that kind any more; and our Paſtor by his good Directions, Prayers, and the power with which Almighty God hath entruſted him, is able (with our concurrence) to adminiſter the beſt Remedy to all our ſins. And then another Perſon, tho' he were not more Learned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no way concerned or intereſted in our Affairs, muſt needs be more void of Paſſion, more Impartial, and Conſequently can better Judge of us, better Direct and Guide us than we our ſelves O that we could thus die to all things but God, and take no pleaſure but in Self-denials and Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications for the ſake of Jeſus: From whence flows that Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity &amp; Purity of heart,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.8.</note> to which our Saviour hath Emphatically annexed the Bleſſedneſs of ſeeing God!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:53294:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The Third <hi>Rule,</hi> Of the <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions</hi> of groſſer <hi>Sins.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THirdly, We are to avoid the Occaſions of the ſins of the Fleſh. Some of them I ſhall name.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1ſt. The mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Proviſion for the Fleſh to fulfill the Luſts thereof.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.14.</note> Strong Meats, ſtrong Drinks, high Sauces are not conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, as being many times very hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Memory and Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, always heightening and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the Paſſions. <hi>Be not drunk with Wine</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi> to his <hi>Epheſians) wherein is Exceſs:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.18.</note> And in Exceſs a Man knows not what he does, but is
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:53294:40"/>
ready to go along with his Company, and to commit with them the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt lewdneſs and outrage whatſoever, under the pretence of a Frolick.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Wherefore Prieſts under the Old Law,</hi> in the time of their Attendance on God in the Execution of their Function, were forbidden ſuch things. And all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians now are in ſome manner <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Prieſts.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10.</note> Great Caution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is to be taken of Invitations and publick Entertainments. It is much ſafer to eat alone, or with few and thoſe Abſtemious Perſons. And then rather mean Diet to be choſen than Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacies, (poor Peoples Children we ſee thrive beſt;) often calling to mind the hard fare of our Lord and his poor Diſciples (whom he choſe poor) <hi>Who fed on Ears of Corn, Barley-Bread,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Fiſh, an Honey-Comb, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the like,</hi> and St. John Baptiſt, <hi>upon Locuſts and Wild-Honey,</hi> and the holy Men of <hi>Egypt</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:53294:41"/>
(according to St. <hi>Jerom</hi>) upon much harder Fare. Often remembring alſo, the All-ſatisfying Food promiſed us in Heaven, which will keep us from ever hungering or thirſting any more. <hi>Bleſſed are they that ſhall eat Bread in the Kingdom of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.9.</note> 
                  <hi>And Bleſſed are they that are called to the Marriage Supper of the Lamb. Lord evermore give us that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Bread that never periſhes, and that Heavenly Water alſo which ſhall be in us a well of Water Springing up to everlaſting Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The great reaſon why we ought (if we intend to avoid the ſins of the Fleſh) to take particular care of living Temperate in our Diet, and of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving frequent Faſtings, eſpecially the Solemn Faſts of the Church, is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by our Eating and Drinking the Fleſh arms and furniſhes it ſelf as it were with new Proviſions for fighting againſt the Spirit: New Matter and Fuel is adminiſtred to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:53294:41"/>
Concupiſcence, and the Brain many times ſo heated as not to be able to make a right Judgment of things. It was after a great Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner when <hi>Herod</hi> for the ſake of a filly Dancing.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 6.21.</note> Girl, conſented to the beheading of the Venerable and Chaſt St. <hi>John Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> as having been an open Enemy to his Inceſtuous Marriage. It was in Drunkenneſs when <hi>Lot</hi> committed double Inceſt with his Two Daughters.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13.</note> And we find all along in Scripture, Drunkenneſs and Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony inſeparable Companions of Luſt. And then the neceſſary Repairs of our Body returning ſo often, we are obliged in a manner to be continually upon our Guard, and to put a Knife to our Throat (as the Wiſe Man adviſeth) that we be not overcome by our Appetite. <q>This Concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in Eating and Drinking (by reaſon of the dayly neceſſities of the Body) is no ſuch thing (ſays St.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:53294:42"/>
                     <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his Confeſſions) which we can reſolve to cut off at once and touch no more as we may do other things.</q> Eat and Drink we muſt, yet not to Exceſs. The reins therefore of the Throat are to be held with a moderate hand between <hi>too little</hi> and <hi>too much; And who is he O Lord</hi> (ſays the ſame Father) <hi>that is not ſometimes tranſported beyond the Liſts of Neceſſity?</hi> Whoever he be, a great one he is, let him magnifie thy Name. So that in one word our liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing temperate and watching over our Appetite, ſo as to thwart it in every thing, is the taking away the chief and moſt principal occaſion of Luſt, and as I may ſay the quenching of it in its very Cauſe. <hi>Fraena gulam, &amp;c.</hi> Bridle your Appetite (ſays <hi>Thomas a Kempie</hi>) and you will the more eaſily bridle every Inclination of the Fleſh.</p>
               <p>To Temperance in Meat and Drink, and frequent Faſtings, we may add Watching and Moderating our Sleep, which (as Experience
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:53294:42"/>
ſhews us) very much tames the Fleſh (as it does even the wildneſs of the moſt ſavage Beaſts) and in a manner pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth the ſame effects upon it as Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, renders us leſs diſpoſed to ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Mirth, and more inclined to Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Recollection. When in Bed, if we cannot ſleep, Praying and Medirating is neceſſary, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times riſing from our Beds (when we cannot otherwiſe drive away impure Thoughts), and paſſing the whole Night under God's wing in Devotions without any ſleep at all, according to the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of our <hi>Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.12. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.16.</note> 
                  <hi>his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,</hi> King <hi>David</hi> and other Saints. For lazy Sleep, and indeed all manner of Sloathfulneſs, is ſo near a kin to Luſt that nothing can break it off but vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and ſtrong reſolutions againſt it: Forcing our ſelves out of our Chair or Couch to ſome Vertuous Action, or Pious Company, or the ordinary buſineſs of our Employments, or what is much better, to our Prayers And
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:53294:43"/>
it is worth all our pains and trouble, if it were only for preſerving our Chaſtity: To which Vertue alone the Two great Monarchs of the World, <hi>Cyrus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> ſeem to have owed the ſucceſs of their Arms; and the Apoſtate <hi>Julian</hi> (when he had left all other Vertues) moſt truly owned that this Queen of Vertues made Lives more Beautiful than Painters Could Faces Fair; and the Reaſon given by <hi>Salvian</hi> of the <hi>Goths</hi> gaining the Empire of <hi>Rome</hi> is, That they were a Nation far more chaſt, and ſent on purpoſe by God to chaſtiſe the Effeminacy of the <hi>Romans:</hi> And yet that Vertue in them ſo Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, how far ſhort came it of true Chriſtian Chaſtity, which ought to be embraced for the ſole ſake of Chriſt, and accompanied alſo with all other Chriſtian Vertues which they wanted. The Truth is, to ſleep and loyter away our time (which is one of the moſt precious Talents with which Almighty God hath entruſted us) is altogether miſpending of it; and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:53294:43"/>
ſo is alſo the paſſing of it in Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, high Gaming, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from whence naturally proceeds Swearing, Curſing, Damning our ſelves and others, all which are far worſe than Idleneſs it ſelf. A diligent Employment therefore, ſuch as together with our Prayers, and the Exigences of Nature, (not excluſive of ſome ſhort innocent Diverſions) meaſures out all our time, is abſolutely requiſite even to the greateſt Perſonages: And the more of it that is ſpent in the Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Service of God the better, as coming nearer the eternal Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Bleſſed in Heaven. But of all the Labours, the reſiſting Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and our Paſſions, and all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements to Sloth and Idleneſs, (ſo frequently recommended to us in Holy Scripture under the Name of Vigilancy and Watching) is the greateſt and moſt worthy a Man; and time is never b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ter ſpent than in ſo doing. <hi>Bleſſed is that Servant whom our Lord when he cometh ſhall find ſo Employed.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 24.46.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:53294:44"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Lewd and Debauched Company, and Filthy Converſation, is alſo to be avoided as a principal occaſion of Luſt. It was an obſervation of the Moraliſt <hi>Seneca</hi> long ago concerning the Temper of the World in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral: <q>That he could never go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in it one day and return home again at night with the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners he carryed out with him; but was ſtill rifled of ſome Vertue or other, and rendred either more ambitious, or more luxurious and the like.</q> Which holds much truer of Lewd and Debauched Company now-a-days, who are the very Scum and Reproach of Mankind, ſetting up (as the Infidels did the Statues of <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Adonis</hi> in the place of the <hi>Holy Croſs</hi>) Debauchery in the place of Piety, and having accuſtomed themſelves to Fleſhly Luſts, perfectly hate all Spiritual Actions and Perſons whatſoever, and knowing the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God againſt the Committers of ſuch things, yet not only do the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:53294:44"/>
ſame, but take pleaſure in them that do them; whoſe very words alſo, and ſometimes breath is contagious; &amp; many times, to keep up &amp; maintain their lewd Courſes, they are forc'd to become common Mercenaries in all ſorts of Wickedneſs to buy themſelves bread (as is notoriouſly evident to the whole World); and you cannot converſe with ſuch without being in danger, either, 1ſt. of partaking of their ſins (which they think only ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary accompliſhments to fit one for their Company) even by not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving them; or, 2dly of being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by their ill Example, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways crying up Liberty and Luxuty againſt Mortification and Chaſtity:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccl.</hi> 13.2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.33</note> Whereas there is no touching of Pitch without being defiled therewith, no having Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with ill manners without being inſenſibly corrupted by them.</p>
               <p>Our Converſation therefore is more ſafe with Vertuous Perſons: And
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:53294:45"/>
thoſe rather few than many; ſuch as may either better us, or we them. But as for open, lewd, prophane Livers, who publiſh their ſin as <hi>Sodom,</hi> glory in their ſhame, boaſt of their Debaucheries as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great Atchievements (as if the Chriſtian Hero was to be known by often violating, not by defending the Bulwarks of Chaſtity) and being perhaps Gentlemen think they are above all Ordinances whatſoever; and ſo having removed all Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks between good and evil, and owning no Obligation to a Supream Power, beſides what is Suggeſted from Nature, profeſs themſelves downright <hi>Libertines,</hi> and count it their greateſt Excellency to have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Vertue nor Religion (which they call Chains and Fetters; whoſe death however is commonly in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire): We are ſtrictly forbidden having any Society with ſuch. I have written to you (ſays St. <hi>Paul</hi> to his <hi>Corinthians) not to keep Company if any Man that is called a Brother be a
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:53294:45"/>
Fornicator, &amp;c.</hi> or a <hi>Drunkard, &amp;c. with ſuch a one no not to Eat.</hi> And this, 1ſt. in order to the bettering of him by making him aſhamed. Or at leaſt, 2ly. for the preſerving our ſelves from being inſenſibly corrupted by him. Or, 3ly. from giving Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal to others by our frequenting ſuch ill Company. Thus St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Mother carried herſelf towards her own Son, who till he had Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced his <hi>Manichaean</hi> Hereſy and Vicious Life together, and become a good Chriſtian, would not ſo much as eat with him; tho nevertheleſs when alone ſhe was almoſt always in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and tears to God for him, till ſhe had obtained his Converſion.</p>
               <p>It is a ſaying of <hi>Matchiavil,</hi> That the ready way to ruine a State or Kingdom is to fill it with ill manners. Good reaſon then for good Men to take care how they Converſe with ill, and to ſuſpect all they do not know; leaſt at length, not only themſelves but the Publick alſo be endamaged
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:53294:46"/>
by it. But then Caſes of neceſſity are to be exempted, when either we or they cannot ſubſiſt or perform our ordinary Duties without our coming together; or there is high Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of our Reforming them by our Converſing friendly and vertuouſly with them. Otherwiſe we are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden all manner of Converſation with ſuch notorious Sinners, ſo long as they continue the Cuſtom and Practice of their lewd and wicked Courſes and ſeem obſtinately reſolved ſo to do: Becauſe our ſiding and herd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with ſuch is plainlly the declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves on the Devils ſide, open Enemies to God and all goodneſs And for this reaſon it is that the Church of Chriſt (like a moſt wiſe Mother) hath in all Ages taken ſtrict care to ſecure her obedient Children from the Infection of the Diſobedient, by making ſevere Canons againſt Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Communicating, and (in ſome Caſes) ſpeaking with the Perverſe, whether their Errors were in Faith or Practice. Becauſe ſhe not diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:53294:46"/>
the hearts of her Children, can only level her Cenſures againſt their External Profeſſion as ſhe perceives them faulty either in Doctrin or Manners; and thoſe that will not be reſtrained, muſt blame, not her, but themſelves, if they incurr her Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema's inſtead of her Bleſſings.<note place="margin">Can. Apoſt.</note> See <hi>Can. Apoſt.</hi> 11, 12, 13. <hi>Conc. Laod. Can.</hi> 33, 38, 39. <hi>Concil. Carthag.</hi> 4. <hi>Can.</hi> 72, 73. St. <hi>Aug. Ep.</hi> 48. and <hi>Ep.</hi> 152.</p>
               <p>To Lewd and Debauched Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany we may add lewd Books, as the worſt and moſt dangerous Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of all: Becauſe they uſually take us alone, and when perhaps leaſt upon our Guard. By lewd Books I mean naſty Ribaldry, Novels, Poems, Songs, Pictures, Romances, and many of our Modern Plays (which of that kind are ſo much the worſe as their Language is better) the Authors whereof (even when they become Penitents) can never (ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:53294:47"/>
ſpeaking) make a ſufficient Satisfaction to God and the World, without a Solemn Retractation of them. Many unwary, both Men and Women, have been ruined by them, none bettered, becauſe indeed they with all the Pomp imaginable recommend the Debauchery they pretend to expoſe; and if you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, always ſpeak more wittily for, than againſt the Vice they are deſcribing. But as bad Books are the worſt, ſo good Books are the beſt Companions in the World: The ſafeſt retreat from ill Company, more advantageous than the beſt, and the greateſt Felicity on this ſide of Heaven. <hi>In omnibus requiem quaeſivi,</hi> &amp;c. I ſought my quiet in all things of this Life, but could not find it, only <hi>in Angello cum libello,</hi> with a little good Book in a convenient Nook.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3ly. Infamous Places (infected with the whole herd or any one of theſe abominable ſins), notwithſtanding their being
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:53294:47"/>
grown almoſt into a Faſhion amongſt us, are to be moſt watchfully avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by us, whether they be ſingle Houſes or whole Cities. No truſting to the ſmooth words of an Harlot, <hi>who layeth in wait at all the Corners of the Streets,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.5.10.16.</note> 
                  <hi>enticing whom ſhe can to her houſe;</hi> pretending all things are made ready for them, when at the ſame time ſhe intends only to make a prey of them. And the ſame Wiles &amp; Crafts may be obſerved in common Drunkards and all profligate Sinners, who are alſo very dexterous in uſing their Witticiſms and little Artifices to deceive and draw in others. <hi>Thomas a Kempis</hi> adviſeth againſt too great Familiarity with any (eſpecially Women) how good ſoever, much more with lewd Perſons, or Cohabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with them. No ſafe venturing into their Houſes where this Leproſie hath been ſpread: No ſecure coming into <hi>Sodom,</hi> even for an Angel. Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <hi>Lot,</hi> or any good Man, muſt not ſtay there when he cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:53294:48"/>
them, leaſt he be conſumed with them. And I ſuppoſe <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> and the other Cities about them, to have been in the ſame condition. And yet we find our Saviour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing greater Woes upon ſome other Cities (in his time of Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing viſibly upon Earth) that had received greater mercies, greater means of Salvation; <hi>We to thee</hi> Chorazin,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.21.</note> 
                  <hi>wo to thee</hi> Bethſaida: <hi>If the mighty works that have been done in you, had been done in</hi> Tyre <hi>and</hi> Sidon <hi>they would have repented long ago, ſitting in Sackcloth and Aſhes.</hi> Therefore it <hi>ſhall be more tollerable for thoſe Cities in the day of Judgment than for you.</hi> And I pray God thoſe Woes may not reach our ungrateful Cities, which have ſeen ſo many of God's mighty Works, and felt ſo many of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Corrections, yet are ſtill ſo over-run with all ſorts of unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſenſuality (as too many profligate Wretches will tell you without bluſhing) that we cannot
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:53294:48"/>
expect leſs than that the utmoſt of the Divine Vengeance ſhould forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with after an extraordinary manner (as lately upon <hi>Jamaica</hi>) be poured out upon us. God's ordinary dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Judgments, ſuch as Plague, Fire, Sword, Poverty, have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed us, and nothing now (as it ſeems to me) but a ſpeedy Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Repentance, like that of <hi>Nineveh,</hi> can avert our ruine. Our good Lord give us ſuch true, univerſal, over-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Repentance, before it be too late.</p>
               <p>Before I conclude this Chapter, give me leave to add one Caution more concerning Diſcourſe, as being the moſt dangerours Occaſion of the filthieſt ſins. All levity therein, fooliſh Talking, Jeſting, Buffoonery, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous Facetiouſneſs, Affectation of Wit and the like, muſt be avoided; becauſe they tend wholly to the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of men, and that many times not without groſly offending of God: and woe to them that (in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner)
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:53294:49"/>
                  <hi>Laugh now, for they ſhall eternally weep here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.25.</note> It is good Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice therefore which is given by a very Learned Perſon upon this Point, to uſe an Holy Reſervedneſs in our Converſation, even with intimate Friends, and not to turn our inſide outward, or to ſpeak all that comes in our thoughts. Becauſe, having ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny imperfections moſt of our thoughts muſt needs be weak and unrefined, and we apprehend at firſt ſight ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Nature, not Grace, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſome Preconſideration be uſed. And in much Company we are to accuſtom our ſelves rather to ſilence (ſometimes impoſing it upon our ſelves if given to talk much) ſo far forth as is conſiſtent with our Duty and Common Civility: And not to permit the lewd or idle Diſcourſe of others to interrupt (as little as may be) our <hi>Praying continually,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.17.</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways giving thanks, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joicing always in the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:53294:49"/>
Lord, which is the true Life and perfection of a Chriſtian. The Guarding thus our own Tongues well and Watching other Mens, cuts off perhaps the greateſt occaſion of our corrupting or being corrupted: As may be ſeen more at large in the many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Diſcourſes upon this Subject, to which I referr the Reader. Subjoining only the warning our Saviour hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us, <hi>That of every idle word we ſpeak</hi> (much more of our Perjuries,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.36, 37.</note> Obſtinacies, palpable Lyes and Blaſphemies) <hi>we muſt give an account at the day of Judgment, and that according to our words we ſhall either be Condemned or Juſtified.</hi> God grant we may not out of our own mouths be condemned in that terrible day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:53294:50"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The Fourth Rule, Of <hi>Divine Aſſiſtances</hi> and the means of obtaining them.</head>
               <p>FOurthly, The laſt Rule I ſhall mention is, The being mindful of the Powerful Aſſiſtances afforded Chriſtians above all others in the Conquering their Luſts, and of the means alſo of obtaining thoſe Aſſiſtances. For it is to be noted, 1ſt. That no one Sin is Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned but by the <hi>Death of Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.3.</note> 2ly. That to the applying the <hi>Merits of Chriſt's Paſſion</hi> to us there are required ſome Conditions on our part,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12.</note> namely our Aſſenting and Co-operating with God's Grace.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:53294:50"/>
3ly. That by ſuch Application not only our ſins are remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.5.4.25.</note> but we receive the <hi>Grace of Regeneration,</hi> changing us in our minds, implanting us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, enabling us to good works,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12.</note> 
                  <hi>to become doers of the Law, Sons of God, &amp;c.</hi> The manner of ſuch our <hi>Regeneration</hi> and of the Divine Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is thus. <hi>Firſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.26.</note> When we are Baptized into Chriſts Church, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſt ſins are waſhed away (ſuppoſing us rightly diſpoſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto) but alſo a new Power and Ability Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural of Living holily for the future is conferr'd and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 11.16</note> The Holy Ghoſt being then perſonally given us, and God's Grace Efficaciouſly plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:53294:51"/>
in us for newneſs of Life,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4.7.6.</note> and bringing forth Good Works. By the Aſſiſtance of this Grace therefore our corrupt Nature is ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly reſtored and made capable of all Vertue, that we may and are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged alſo therewith totally to ſubdue our Luſts; ſo as to live free from the habit even of unclean thoughts,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24.</note> and from the commiſſion of all unclean Acts, at leaſt of thoſe greater before mentioned, which we are ſure (from God's own Word) exclude the Kingdom of Heaven. By this new principle of Grace,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.5.</note> which work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with us, (and without which our working ſignifies nothing) a real Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, &amp; Facility to Good, is conveyed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Souls; our Underſtanding is Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated ſo as readily to embrace the Holy Myſteries of Chriſt's Religion which are above it, above it's natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Knowledge and Reach, and paſt its ever finding out but by Revelation: Our Will from time to time inſpired
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:53294:51"/>
with new and divine Affections and at length influenced (at leaſt in ſome Perſons) with an impatient Love of God above all other things. And the ſame Holy Spirit, which thus Acts and Aſſiſts within us, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceeds alſo for us,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26.</note> 
                  <hi>with groans which cannot be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered:</hi> groans irreſiſtably prevalent at the Throne of Grace.</p>
               <p>To the firſt Grace therefore given us at our Baptiſm, if we make a right uſe of it, more and more is added (<hi>to every one that hath [improved his one Talent] more ſhall be given,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.29.</note> 
                  <hi>and he ſhall have abundance:</hi>) And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to the ſame well-diſpoſed Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon are conferred ſeveral <hi>Talents,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral different Gifts (for God's greater glory) of the ſame Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; but yet the moſt excellent Grace which we are above all to <hi>covet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.31.</note> as being that without which all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Graces ſignify nothing to us, is,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13</note> 
                  <hi>Charity
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:53294:52"/>
or the Love of God:</hi> Which is the moſt effectual remedy of all our Luſts or falſe Loves, and when once obtained does in a manner the whole work of a Chriſtian it felf, becauſe by its ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret <hi>Energy</hi> it centers all our Affections in our Lord, ſo as ſweetly to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell us to ſeek in all things a punctual Obſervance and conformity to his holy Will, and in nothing to diſpleaſe him, with whom our Soul being raviſhed is <hi>ſick of love for him</hi> and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth with a perpetual deſire,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.8.</note> either, 1ſt. of ſuffering for him (thereby at once to ſhew the Truth of our love and to purify us as Gold in a burning Furnace;) Or, 2ly. of praying to Him (the only way of Converſing with him upon Earth); Or, 3ly. Of fully enjoying him in Heaven, even though it were through Martyrdom it ſelf. Which great Vertue ſhined moſt Eminently in St. <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> whoſe ſins which were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were therefore forgiven her, becauſe ſhe loved much: And her choſing <hi>to ſit
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:53294:52"/>
at the feet of Jeſus to hear his words,</hi> our Saviour himſelf calls the <hi>unum neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> the better and ſublimer part of a Chriſtian, which nothing can take away.</p>
               <p>And albeit this love of God inferrs and comprehends the love of our Neighbour, and of our ſelves, and of all things that belong to God, yet theſe not after the faſhion of the World, but only as conſiſtent with and much encreaſing and enflaming our love of God. So that by ſhewing our love to God (as we are obliged) all the ways that we can, we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually enlivening and augmenting it, and ſtill think it little and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of eternal life; and that it is want of our Endeavours, and not of God's Grace, which hinders us from at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining ſtill higher Spiritual Gifts and a more intenſe love of our Lord; every little Inclination in us to any thing elſe, if not throughly mortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, being enough to retard our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs in this true way to perfection: <hi>This one thing I do</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:53294:53"/>
to his <hi>Philippians) for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geting thoſe things which are behind</hi> [already ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained] <hi>and reaching forward to thoſe things which are before</hi> [not yet obtained] <hi>I preſs toward the</hi> Mark <hi>for the price of the high cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.13.</note> And if ſo great an Apoſtle, when he had ſo far attained as perhaps none farther, in the Love of God and Self-mortifications (wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs his <hi>Watchings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.5.11.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Labours, Stripes, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments, Deaths</hi>) was ſtill preſſing forward; much more ought we to mend our pace who are ſo far behind, ſo far from perfect Charity and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Chaſtity as to be ſtill wallowing in our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſts, ſtill hankering after the Gratifications of Senſe. We ought not only to be mindful of the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Aſſiſtances God hath afforded us to Purity and Holineſs, but alſo actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to make uſe of them for that very end and purpoſe; thoſe Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of the Holy Spirit being ſuch
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:53294:53"/>
as <hi>continually war againſt the Fleſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1.</note> ſtirring us up to ſeek thoſe things that are above and ſupernatural; and ſo after an ineffable manner (if we endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to correſpond to them) unite us to Chriſt and God and bring down Heaven into our Souls, quenching in us the thirſt to all ſenſual Pleaſures, making them by degrees ſeem more and more contemptible to us and at length odious: <hi>Quas ſordes, quae dede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cora,</hi> &amp;c. what filthineſs did they Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, what diſgrace and diſhonour? ſays St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his Confeſſions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his formerly beloved, but then much more hated, Luſts.</p>
               <p>The way therefore to experience the good of Chriſtianity, is reſolutely to enter upon practiſing Chriſtian Vertue by a more ſtrict obſervance of Gods Laws, and purging our ſelves from the contrary Vices. For none (how learned ſoever) can truly know God, but they that ſerve him: And a poor Shepherd, that faithfully
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:53294:54"/>
ſerves him, will by experience know more of God in his chiefeſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, than a Doctor of the Chair that does only talk of him. And as the Grace of God is the principal Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a good Chriſtian Life; ſo the next to that, is frequent examining our Conſciences, once or twice a day; that ſo we may learn to know by little and little how to diſtinguiſh between the motions of Grace and thoſe of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, what are Temptations and what not (and here the Judgment of ſome wiſe conſcientious man more skilful than our ſelves is to be taken in) leaſt we ſhould place our greateſt Conſolation (as the Soul always does in ſomething) in any thing that is not God. We are to think our ſelves below all, and that there are none more frail than our ſelves; to empty our ſelves of all affections to Earthly things, and to have no propriety or deſire that ſhall in the leaſt wiſe hinder our love to God from being pure: To leave our Luſts and that forever, which tho' with St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> we may
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:53294:54"/>
find difficult, yet with him alſo we ſhall thereby find our ſelves freed from a Chain: To be ſo indifferent, laſtly, to joy or ſorrow, Temptation or quietneſs, Life or Death, and all things in this World, as to expect no Conſolation here but what flows from the Croſs. This is dying to our ſelves and all Creatures, that we may be united to God; which the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures call partaking of the Divine Nature,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> turning our heart to God, conformity to his Holy Will, walking in the Truth, ſerving him with a pure mind (<hi>i. e.</hi> without anxiety or Expectation of reward) rejoicing in him, acquieſcing in him,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1.</note> going out of our ſelves into him by a perfect Abnegation of our ſelves,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark</hi> 8.34.</note> referring all things to his Glory and making him all in all to us,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 25.28 <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.6.</note> which is the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Religion, as may be ſeen more at large in <hi>Thomas a Kempis</hi> and other Spiritual Books.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:53294:55"/>But then in our endeavouring after this perfection we muſt beware of the higheſt cunning and muſt ſubtile De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Devil, which the Scripture calls his <hi>transforming himſelf into an Angel of Light.</hi> And that is either, 1ſt. By his ſtirring up in us a ſecret ſelf-conceit of our good Actions as if they could not poſſibly be mended. Or, 2ly. His throwing in ſome little ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Reaſonings and Fallacies to make us abate or alter them (as he always pretends) for the better and for God's greater Glory. For exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; in the exerciſe of our Charity towards our Neighbour, to corrupt that Divine Love, he uſually ſuggeſts ſomething from Reaſon to induce us to change Divine into Rational; then ſomething from Nature to change Natural into Carnal, then ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from our Fleſh alone to change Rational into Natural, till by degrees he renders that love in us, which was at firſt Divine and Pure, altogether impure and unchaſt and moſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite and moſt diſpleaſing to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:53294:55"/>
God. But yet for the moſt part he takes care not to deface all Vertue in his Servants, that neither themſelves nor others may eaſily diſcern the wickedneſs he intermixes, and ſo be frightned into Repentance. Such are the Wiles of the <hi>Roaring Lyon who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually goes about ſeeking how to devour and make a prey of us:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet</hi> v. 9.</note> Whom we are commanded to reſiſt ſtedfaſt in the Faith with all ſobriety and watchfulneſs: But do thou O Lord, have mercy on us and ſtrengthen us to overcome him.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, The means now of obtaining far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Aſſiſtances of the Holy Spirit, beſides what we receive in Baptiſm are chiefly, 1ſt. Prayer, our own and other mens.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.19.</note> 2ly. Frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Communicating. If we would (for Example) obtain in oppoſition to our Luſts (thoſe falſe Loves) that moſt excellent Gift of loving God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:53294:56"/>
all things (which is the) only true love) and doing every thing to pleaſe him,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> we muſt <hi>Firſt,</hi> Pray for it. And this we cannot do with that earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and integrity we ought, before we ſincerely repent of our Falſe Loves, our Darling Luſts. For God hears not unrepenting Sinners, and admits of no Rivals in our Affections, he will have our whole heart or none. Then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our deep ſorrowing for thoſe Heinous Sins (and what ſins are not heinous?) Even ſo ſorrowing as not to be content without the Abſolution of the Church. (See Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi>'s Sermon on <hi>John</hi> 20.23. <hi>Whoſe ſins ye remit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.23.</note> &amp;c.) &amp; to be ready to ſubmit to her ſevereſt Diſcipline for the good of our Souls (See the Preface to the Commination in the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book,) in great Humility and Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of Mind and Self-abjection, and with a ſtedfaſt Lively Faith alſo, that God both Can and Will anſwer our Requeſt if it be for our Good, we
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:53294:56"/>
may again and again diſcover to him our particular Follies (which he alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy knows, but yet expects to be as it were anew Informed of them by us) bemoaning our vileneſs, and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him our preſent wants with all the Motives which we can think will cauſe true Contrition in us, and incline Him alſo to Grant our inſtant Petition. We deſire (for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) what he commands us, the loving Him above all things. Let us lay before Him, beſides our own weakneſſes and Infirmities, his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, Beauty, Wiſdom, Love and Mercy towards us, which one would think were enough to excite our love to him without his commanding us to love him who are moſt unworthy of his love. So many Bleſſings, ſo many Deliverances both Temporal and Spiritual, will they not move us? Hath he not Redeemed us from all our Enemies, the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil? taught us what to do and what to refrain? given us tender Conſciences (the greateſt Bleſſing
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:53294:57"/>
upon Earth) to admoniſh us? En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled us by his Holy Spirit to perform what he requires? And yet when we continue vitious, is he not ſtill patient and long-ſuffering for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance? Preventing our Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with his Grace, renewing his I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage in us, and making us again capable of Immortality and Glory? For all which Benefits, and Ten Thouſand more, can we do leſs than pray we may hate our Selves, our Luſts and all things elſe, and become Dead to ſenſuality and the World for love of him, <hi>who firſt loved us even to Death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some there are and always have been, who by Aſſiduous Praying, having attained to the love of God, think Prayer the greateſt pleaſure of their whole Life, and themſelves ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver well but when they are thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing with Almighty God (whom they reverentially apprehend to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways with them, either before, or within them:) And are continually
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:53294:57"/>
offering to him his own moſt precious Gifts, which he therefore vouchſafes them that they may have ſomething valuable and worthy to offer: And ſo by their Devotions they alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare their Souls for the receiving thoſe particular Graces, for which they pray, and of which they ſtand in need.</p>
               <p>The Power and Prevalency of Prayer (whether Vocal or Mental) with Almighty God, and the great benefits to ourſelves and others from the ſeveral parts thereof, Self-Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, Confeſſion, Thankſgiving, Petition, Praiſe, Reſolution, Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, Oblation, and every kind of Devotion wherein we either ſpeak to God or God to us, together with proper Forms and Directions for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry occaſion, the Reader may amply learn from the publick Liturgies, Manuals, Catechiſms, Lives, and Devotions of holy Men, <hi>&amp;c</hi> written and allowed of by the Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the whole Church of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:53294:58"/>
God in all Ages. And then, as to the neceſſity of Prayer, if we conſider our many wants, Temporal and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, to be relieved; many ſins, wherein we ſtill offend God, to be pardoned; many Temptations and Dangers from which to be preſerved; many Benefits and Aſſiſtances receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and all theſe with a reſpect al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to our Fellow Chriſtians; we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but acknowledge every moment of our Lives (had we no other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Duties) too little to be ſpent in this one Great Duty of <hi>Continual Prayer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.17.</note> Our good Lord aſſiſt us by his Holy Spirit in the diligent and ſincere performance thereof.</p>
               <p>The other Chief Means of our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Divine Aſſiſtances againſt our Luſts; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> is, 2ly. Frequen Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating (as many good Chriſtians now do, and the Primitive Chriſtians did almoſt every day). I do not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend here to treat largely of this Holy Sacrament (there being many good Books Written deſignedly on that Subject,) but only recommend to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:53294:58"/>
the Reader (without medling with God's power therein which tranſcends all Humane Conception and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion) the Immenſe Benefit of this Holy Myſtery to each worthy Communicant in reference to his particular Neceſſities. For obtaining Remiſſion of this or that Sin; a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy of this or that Infirmity; a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from this or that Affliction; for receiving a Benefit, or giving thanks for a Benefit received; for helping our Neighbour; for encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Holy Spirit and Love of God in us. Becauſe, as by one Spirit in Baptiſm, <hi>We are made one Myſtical Body of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13</note> ſo likewiſe, in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, are we made to drink into [the partaking of] one Spirit: The Bleſſed Euchariſt being as neceſſary for the continuing and encreaſing, as Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm for the firſt receiving the Holy Spirit. Becauſe alſo, this is that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Nouriſhment inſtituted by Chriſt for the preſerving our Body and Soul to Everlaſting Life; that
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:53294:59"/>
particular Pledge and Aſſurance of our Reſurrection; <hi>that true Bread from Heaven,</hi> which myſtically alſo In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporates us into Chriſt, and makes us continue and grow up into perfect Members of his Body, that ſo thus partaking of the Nature and Spirit of the <hi>Second Adam, the Heir of all things,</hi> we may become with him <hi>Sons of God, Heirs of Eternal Life,</hi> as we were by the <hi>Firſt Adam, of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Death. That true Heavenly Bread,</hi> laſtly, ſo Exalting and Aſſimulating our Nature into Chriſt (when wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily Communicating) as to make us one with him, <hi>as he and the Father are one:</hi> According to our Saviour's Prayer when he was Inſtituting this Bleſſed Sacrament. <hi>I pray thee Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 17.</note> 
                  <hi>that they may be one, as we are one.</hi> O Bleſſed Union between poor Man and his Maker! O happy thoſe Souls who here worthily feed on this Heavenly Bread, the only true Nouriſhment of the Life of Grace,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:53294:59"/>
enabling them in the Strength there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to walk even to the Mount of God, the Life of Glory.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:53294:60"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The</hi> Concluſion.</head>
            <p>THE Summ of this Diſcourſe is, The Sins of the Fleſh are moſt dangerous, becauſe moſt natural, to us: And by reaſon of their filthineſs moſt loathſome to Almighty God, and moſt ſeverely puniſhed by him. For not only thoſe of the greater mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude, Fornication, Adultery, Inceſt, Sodomy, Beaſtiality, are followed with God's moſt Tremendous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; but alſo we find in Scripture <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs</hi> and <hi>Laciviouſneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.3.</note> deſtinct from the foregoing, and of a leſs denomination, every where joyned with ſuch Sins as exclude the Practiſers thereof from the Kingdom of Heaven. The way to prevent ſuch Sins and to avoid the puniſhment of them, is, To mortify our Paſſions, our Memory and Imagination; to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:53294:60"/>
beware of impure Suggeſtions, cheirſh Holy Inſpirations, and avoid all the occaſions of ſuch Sins; to Improve, laſtly, the Grace of God in us by Aſſiduous Prayer, daily Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſelves, perfect Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, frequent Communicating and all other holy means; preſſing ſtill farther to higher and higher Gifts, particularly to the attaining that moſt excellent Gift of Charity, which makes us love God above all things, and our Neighbour as our ſelves; hate even our own Lives for love of Him who firſt loved us, undergoing the the greateſt ſufferings with Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Complacency, perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all our Actions on purpoſe to pleaſe him, referring them to his Honour, offering them up to his Praiſe and Glory: To whom Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, be all Honour, Praiſe and Glory to all Eternity, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:53294:61"/>
               <hi>God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth,</hi> Joh. 4.24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grace and Truth</hi> [i. e. means of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation] <hi>came by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Joh. 1.17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God ſent forth the Spirit of his Son into our hearts, that they that live, ſhould not henceforth live unto themſelves, but to him who dyed for them,</hi> Gal. 4.6. 2 Cor. 5.15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wretched is that man who is all for the good things of this Life, a good Houſe, good Apparel, good Proviſion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and is content to have a bad Soul.</hi> Int. Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:53294:61"/>
            <head>Some Short Directions and Heads of Meditation for the Perſons Concerned in the Preceeding Diſcourſe.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of <hi>Meditation,</hi> it's <hi>Requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites,</hi> and how it differs from <hi>Contemplation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MEditation</hi> is called the firſt Eſſential part of Prayer, leading to <hi>Contemplation, Thanksgiving, Petition, &amp;c.</hi> in which all the Principal Faculties of the Soul, the <hi>Memory, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Will,</hi> and <hi>Affections,</hi> are ſeverally employed.
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:53294:62"/>
The <hi>Memory</hi> recollects the matter to be Meditated upon, and alſo placeth the Soul in the Divine Preſence: The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> judgeth of the <hi>Subject</hi> and its <hi>Vertues,</hi> and accordingly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth it to the <hi>Will.</hi> The <hi>Will</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites in, us divers <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Affections,</hi> either of <hi>Love, Affiance, Gratitude,</hi> &amp;c. towards God: Or of <hi>Hatred, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction, deſire of doing better,</hi> &amp;c. towards our ſelves, which is indeed the main Scope and end of <hi>Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Then follows our Praying and repreſenting to Almighty God our Miſeries, Neceſſities, Temptations, which we moſt earneſtly beg him to redreſs for his own Love and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion's ſake, and the Merits of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. But when the Faculties of the Soul are unactive or ſlow in their Operations (as it often happens) they are to be excited by the help of <hi>good Books,</hi> which ought always to be at hand when we Meditate: and in all ſuch holy exerciſe we are to approach the Divine Preſence with our great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:53294:62"/>
Reverence and Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>And it is alſo neceſſary before eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Meditation, to make a ſtrict <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> of Conſcience 1. What Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits we have received that day from Almighty God; for which we are to return Thanks. 2. What Sins we have that day committed (run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning through every hour) in thought, word and deed; for which we are to beg pardon. 3. We are to reſolve upon an amendment in every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular by the Grace of God. After ſuch ſtrict Examination of all our Thoughts, Deſires, Words and Works, judging our ſelves that we be not judged of the Lord; and Confeſſing our Sins in the bitterneſs of our Soul as the Church requires, and taking alſo revenge of our ſelves according to the Example of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Penitent amongſt the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> we ſhall by ſuch fifting our Conſciences be the better able to ſever the Wheat from the Chaff, and know alſo what is fitteſt to <hi>offer</hi> to Almighty God, what
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:53294:63"/>
to <hi>pray</hi> for, and what alſo to <hi>meditate</hi> upon.</p>
               <p>In which particular <hi>Examen</hi> of our Conſciences (wherein we are to endeavour to produce Acts of Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Self-confuſion, Humility, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions of amendment, Reſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) we muſt obſerve to what Vice we are moſt inclined, and be ſure to bend all our Forces againſt it; for that <hi>Captain-Imperfection</hi> being Conquered, the reſt will eaſily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit: And in the next <hi>Examen,</hi> we muſt Impartially enquire whether our relapſes in that kind are as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent as formerly, and ſo continue on the Fight with new Fervour, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour and Conſtancy, till it ſhall pleaſe God to give us the Victory.</p>
               <p>Now the difference between <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> and <hi>Contemplation</hi> is ſaid by holy Men to be as follows. 1. We <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate</hi> when by the help of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> we ſeek and caſt about, and at length fix our thoughts upon ſuch
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:53294:63"/>
Truths and Reaſons as are in our preſent Circumſtances, moſt apt to move and affectionate the <hi>Will,</hi> to the embracing the Love of God, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Vertues, Works of Piety, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but ſometimes the Inclinations of the <hi>Will</hi> (the Holy Spirit operating more principally in <hi>that</hi> by <hi>Love,</hi> than in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> by <hi>Illumination;</hi>) preceed the Acts of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> tho' moſt commonly it is the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, the <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Paſſions</hi> not eaſily moving without the <hi>Reaſoning</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> to excite them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We <hi>Contemplate</hi> when we ſtead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly and unmovably behold God by <hi>Faith,</hi> believing that he is really with us and within us (as he truly is); and ſo leaving all other Objects, Idea's, and Diſcourſes, we Internally look on him as preſent, love him in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and feed on his All-ſatiating Sweetneſs. And this Contemplation is either by the help of <hi>Senſible</hi> Idea's, or <hi>Intelligible,</hi> or ſurmounts them both, which is the higheſt ſort of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:53294:64"/>
Prayer. But this is not my buſineſs at preſent, I intending only ſome ſhort Meditations, ſuch as the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er may eaſily carry about with him, even in his Memory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:53294:64"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the <hi>Subject</hi> of <hi>Meditation,</hi> with Heads for the firſt Week.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Subject</hi> of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation may be any thing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Divinely revealed, or that any way conduceth to our Salvation. But moſt commonly it is adapted to the Three Degrees of Chriſtians, <hi>the lower, the middle, and the higheſt.</hi> Some Learned Men recommend the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of the Church in her <hi>Liturgies,</hi> beginning with <hi>Advent, Nativity</hi> of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and ſo on to his <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Paſſion, Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, ſending the Holy Spirit,</hi> taking in the Epiſtles and Goſpels of all the <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi>'s and <hi>Holy-Days.</hi> This Rule is Chiefly obſerved by the Clergy. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:53294:65"/>
adviſe the Selecting ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain number of <hi>pious Subjects</hi> for every day in the Week, and keeping to them only, and this ſeems alſo a very uſeful way of Meditation.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Heads of <hi>Meditation</hi> for the firſt Week.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Monday <hi>Of the Chief end of Man.</hi>
                     </hi> Conſider, 1. Why he was Created; namely, to praiſe and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2 How far this is obſerved or tranſgreſſed by us, and how far the ample means offorded thereunto abuſed. <hi>Reflexion</hi> 1. Give God Thanks. 2. Ask Pardon. 3. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe Amendment in every particular as need requires.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tueſday. <hi>Of God's Benefits.</hi>
                     </hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, our <hi>Being</hi> from God, Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, Redemption, Sanctification, Spiritual Gifts, and Graces, the Holy Sacraments, Eternal Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:53294:65"/>
that God gives is freely out of his own Goodneſs, not for his own but our profit. <hi>Reflex.</hi> 1. Give great Thanks with all poſſible Humility. 2. Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up your ſelf, all your Thoughts, Words, Actions and Affections to God, to be ſincerely directed to his Glory only.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wedneſday. <hi>Of your Sins.</hi>
                     </hi> Conſider, 1. Who it is you have offended, <hi>viz. God</hi> moſt <hi>Munificent,</hi> who hath done ſo many and ſo great things for you, and promiſed more and greater. 2. <hi>God Omniſcient,</hi> who ſees all things moſt clearly. 3. <hi>God Omnipotent,</hi> who can deſtroy you in a moment, and none is able to reſiſt him. 4. <hi>God moſt Pure,</hi> who abhors all ſin; and for that Reaſon threw the fallen Angels out of Heaven for one ſingle Sin. <hi>Adam</hi> out of <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> and condemned him to above 900 Years Pennance for one ſingle diſobedience. <hi>Reflect.</hi> What then will become of Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Sinners? And how great Reaſon to Fear and Tremble at ſo great Power and Juſtice of God!</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:53294:66"/>Conſider, 2. Who <hi>thou</hi> art that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend'ſt and reſiſteſt ſo great a God? A moſt vile &amp; inconſiderable Worm. The whole World in God's ſight is but as a drop of the morning dew. <hi>Sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</hi> 11. What is man then ſo minute a Particle of that Drop? Who is indeed nothing of himſelf, and compared to Infinity bears no Proportion. <hi>Reflect.</hi> How great the Clemency of God in bearing ſo long with ſo great Sinners, and your ſelf the Chief, and very greateſt of all.</p>
                  <p>Conſider, 3. For <hi>what Cauſe</hi> you offended God? For ſome very vile thing, ſome vain Honour, ſome beaſtly pleaſure; and that knowing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wilfully, not out of Ignorance or Infirmity. <hi>Reflect.</hi> Deteſt thy Fooliſhneſs before God. Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thy Fault. Beg mercy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thurſday. <hi>Of Death,</hi>
                     </hi> Conſider. 1. The certainty of it, and the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the time. Recollect all the ſuddain Deaths you have ever ſeen,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:53294:66"/>
heard, or read of, and conclude it the greateſt madneſs and folly in the World to live on in ſuch a State in which you would not die. <hi>Reflect.</hi> You can die but <hi>once,</hi> and if not <hi>well</hi> your loſs is irreparable.</p>
                  <p>Conſider. 2. Of <hi>what things</hi> Death deprives you. Of all External things, Riches, Pleaſures, Honours, Friends, for which and whoſe ſake you have ſo often offended God. And that nothing will accompany you to the other World, but your works whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good or bad. <hi>Reflect.</hi> Imagine what a wicked man reſtored to Life from Hell-fire would do, and that do you.</p>
                  <p>Conſider, 3. The State of your <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Soul.</hi> Your Body (for which you have been ſo Sollicitous) will be carryed out to be meat for the <hi>Worms,</hi> your Soul immediately hurri'd to Judgment by the Angels, and from thence by an unknown way to an eternal State either of bleſs, or miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:53294:67"/>
according to the Actions done in the Fleſh. <hi>Reflect.</hi> Uſe now all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible means by your ſelf and others to make Chriſt (who is to be your Judge) become propitious to you: And pray to God for Grace that you may now both know and do what upon your Death-bed and at the Judgment Seat you will wiſh you had done.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Friday, <hi>Of the laſt Judgment.</hi>
                     </hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, 1. The particular Judgment that paſſeth upon every man at his Death, and remains unalterable. 2. The dreadfulneſs of the laſt general day, when the Heavens will be roul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together as a Scrol, the Sun it ſelf darkened, the Moon not give her light, the Stars fall from their <hi>Orbs,</hi> the Earth quake, the Mountains and Iſlands remove out of their places, and Mens hearts fail them for fear. 3. An Univerſal appearance of all the Sons of <hi>Adam</hi> (the Earth and Sea giving up their Dead) and a particular Examination of them
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:53294:67"/>
according to God's unerring Books which will then be opened.</p>
                  <p>Conſider, 4. <hi>The Difference</hi> that will then be between the Good and Bad. The Good (having Co-operated with God's Grace) ſhall be Cloathed with Glorious Bodies, and placed on Chriſt's Right Hand. The Bad (not Co-operating with God's Spirit) Cloathed with Corruption, and placed on Chriſt's Left Hand. And the Conſciences and Thoughts of all hearts will be then laid open. <hi>Reflect.</hi> What ſhame, &amp; confuſion will it then be to the Impenitent, when out of their own Mouths and Conſciences they will be both Accuſed and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned!</p>
                  <p>Conſider, 5. How aſtoniſhing it will be to the <hi>Wicked,</hi> to hear the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the <hi>Judge, Go, ye Curſed, into everlaſting Fire.</hi> And how joyful to the Righteous to hear, <hi>Come, ye bleſſed, poſſeſs the Kingdom prepared for you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Reflect.</hi> Make firm Purpoſes to live
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:53294:68"/>
well, and in vertuous Circumſtances; and intreat the Judge to be propitious to you, and that you may always bear in mind this terrible Judgment and Sentence to eſcape it, which is ſaid to have occaſioned the Inſtitution of the ſevereſt Order of Chriſtians in the World.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saturday. <hi>Of Hell.</hi>
                     </hi> Conſider, 1. What a Puniſhment it would be to be bound Hand and Foot, and caſt into a hot fiery Furnace, there to remain burning and unconſumed, tho but for a ſhort time: And as every Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Body, ſo every Power and Faculty of the Soul receive its peculiar Torment.</p>
                  <p>Conſider, 2. How hard and unſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable it muſt needs be to be <hi>Slaves</hi> to the Devils and Companions of the damned, amidſt the moſt exquiſit, <hi>Tortures,</hi> and inceſſant Blaſphemies and Curſings of Allmighty God.</p>
                  <p>Conſider, 3. How long theſe Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:53294:68"/>
will laſt. If after ſome Thouſands of Years there were to be an end, it would ſomewhat leſſen them: But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an Hundred thouſand Years ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds an Eternity that cannot be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reflect.</hi> How fooliſh is it to chuſe ſuch endleſs Torments for a tranſitory Pleaſure. Endure any Puniſhments here to avoid them. <hi>Here cut, here burn, but ſave me in the World to come,</hi> was St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Prayer. Entreat Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God that you may be ſo aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them, whilſt living, that you may not deſerve to experience them when dead.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sunday. <hi>Of the Joys of Heaven.</hi>
                     </hi> Conſider, 1. The <hi>Place</hi> and the <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</hi> How great Joy it muſt needs be to inhabit in the City of God, the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and converſe with the holy Angels, and all the Saints which have been from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the World: Who having the ſame Charity one for another
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:53294:69"/>
(being all filled with the ſame holy Spirit) rejoyce in every ones Good as if it were their own.</p>
                  <p>Conſider, 2. The greatneſs of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> The Body it ſelf will be ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualized, and all its Senſes and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers exalted and adorned with moſt admirable Gifts. And the Soul en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to ſee and know God as he is, and to love and enjoy him to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which is the only true Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And though there be far different degrees of Glory, yet no Envy, but on the contrary Rejoycing. See the preceeding Diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reflect.</hi> Give God thanks, who hath given you to hope for, and made you capable of this Glory; and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly implore him mercifully to preſerve you (though ungrateful) in true Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and holy Living, that you may at length come to that glorious Place, and there praiſe and magnify him to all Eternity.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:53294:69"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Heads of <hi>Meditation</hi> for the Second, Third, and Fourth Weeks.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Second Week.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MOnday.</hi> Of the <hi>Incarnation</hi> of our Saviour. His leaving the Boſom of his Father, and taking upon him Humane Nature Voluntarily, and yet by conſent of the whole Trinity. A Mercy denied to the fallen Angels: And a Myſtery which the good Angels deſired to look into.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tueſday.</hi> Of the <hi>Viſitation</hi> of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-Bleſſed Virgin, and the Saluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Angel. <hi>Hail, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> Of the <hi>Nativity</hi> of our
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:53294:70"/>
Lord in a <hi>Stable,</hi> yet honoured with Miracles.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thurſday.</hi> Of the <hi>Shepherd</hi>'s <hi>Viſion,</hi> the <hi>Angels Hymn,</hi> the coming of the <hi>Three Kings</hi> by the Guidance of a Star or Angel.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Friday.</hi> Of the <hi>Offering up</hi> of our Saviour in the Temple. The <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility</hi> of the Mother of our Lord, being not obliged to any ſuch Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Old <hi>Simeon</hi>'s Prayer, <hi>Lord now letteſt, &amp;c.</hi> He could not die till he had ſeen the Lords Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saturday.</hi> Our Saviour's <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the Teſtimony the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> then gave of his Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sunday.</hi> Of our Lord's <hi>Transfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guration</hi> and the Conſolation the Three Diſciples alſo took therein. <hi>It is good for us to be here, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:53294:70"/>
                  <head>The Third Week.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MOnday.</hi> Of the <hi>Eight Beatitudes,</hi> the Sum of Chriſtian Perfection; placing happineſs in things ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moſt contrary to it, ſuch as Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Perſecution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But yet the true and only way to Bleſſedneſs, declared to be ſo by him who is Wiſdom it ſelf, and who himſelf alſo became our Example in ſufferings.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tueſday.</hi> Of the <hi>Lord's Prayer;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining all the good things we are to pray for, and all the evils we are to pray againſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> Of the <hi>Rich Glutton</hi> and the ten <hi>Virgins.</hi> The difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Dives</hi> and <hi>Lazarus,</hi> both in this World and the other: And between the ten Virgins in the other World, notwithſtanding their ſeeming equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:53294:71"/>
                     <hi>Thurſday.</hi> Of the <hi>Converſion</hi> of <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> and the Woman of <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.</hi> Both of them great Sinners. The former poſſeſſed with ſeven Devils, and the latter lived in Fornication. But their Repentance was as remarkable as their Sins: And their after life as Vertuous, as their former had been Vicious.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Friday.</hi> Of the <hi>Paralytick</hi> at the Pool of <hi>Betheſda;</hi> and of the Man born blind. Both cured by our Saviour: And both afterwards openly Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him. To leave our ſins and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt, takes away the Cauſe of Sin: For there is a Lameneſs and Blindneſs alſo in the Soul.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saturday.</hi> Of the <hi>Prodigal Son,</hi> and the <hi>Man</hi> that fell among Thieves. The Prodigal was received by his Father upon his returning and repenting. The poor Man fell among Thieves by his leaving his right way, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for <hi>Jericho,</hi> God for his pleaſure, the Church for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Thieves and Robbers. <hi>Reflect.</hi> Converſion to God's Church and Repentance the only Remedy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:53294:71"/>
                     <hi>Sunday.</hi> Of our Saviour's raiſing from the Dead <hi>Lazarus,</hi> the <hi>Son</hi> of the Woman of <hi>Naim,</hi> the <hi>Daughter</hi> of <hi>Jairus.</hi> One of them was newly dead, the ſecond carried out, the third three days buried. The newly dead immediately upon our Saviour's ſpeaking, roſe and walked &amp; was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly cured, the reſt not ſo ſoon. <hi>Reflect.</hi> So it fairs with Sinners. More diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty for habituated Sinners to riſe to a Life of Grace.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Fourth Week.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MOnday.</hi> Of the Inſtitution of the <hi>Bleſſed Euchariſt.</hi> He that Eats worthily of this <hi>Bread</hi> ſhall live for ever, ſhall overcome his Luſts, be filled with Celeſtial Joys, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But he that Eats unworthily eats his own Damnation (if he dies in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition) not diſcerning the Lord's Body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:53294:72"/>
                     <hi>Tueſday.</hi> Of our Saviour's <hi>Paſſion</hi> in General. Who it was that ſuffered? The Son of God, God himſelf, Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What and how grievous things he ſuffered? So many griefs. So great Ignominy. He hath born our griefs. Behold the Man. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and ſee, were there ever ſufferings like his? And all this for his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, (ungrateful ſinners, and me in particular) to Reconcile them to God. <hi>Reflect.</hi> Oh the Obedience, Humility, Patience, Perſeverance, Charity of his ſufferings!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> What paſſed in the Garden. His Agony. His Soul was heavy even to Death. He ſweat drops of Blood. He Prayed againſt the bitter Cup, but with a Reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his Fathers Will. <hi>Thy will not mine be done.</hi> And ſoon after with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallell'd Fortitude ſurrendred him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>If you ſeek me let theſe go their ways,</hi> deſiring to tread the Wine-preſs of God's Wrath alone.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:53294:72"/>
                     <hi>Thurſday.</hi> Our Saviour's <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Annas, Caiphas, Herod,</hi> and <hi>Pilate.</hi> Before <hi>Annas</hi> Queſtioned for his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. In <hi>Caiphas</hi>'s houſe falſe Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes were brought againſt him. He was kept Priſoner there all Night. Mockt by the Souldiers and others. Denyed by <hi>Peter.</hi> Before <hi>Herod</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed. Before <hi>Pilate</hi> firſt declared Innocent, but afterwards Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by him for Treaſon, to pleaſe the People and ſecure his own Intereſt with them. St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Repentance very ſpeedy. But the Obſtinacy of the <hi>Jews</hi> continues to this very day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Friday.</hi> Our Saviour's <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage</hi> at the Pillar; his <hi>Crown of Thorns;</hi> his <hi>Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> to Mount <hi>Calvary</hi> bearing his Croſs; his barbarous <hi>Crucifixion,</hi> the <hi>Wounds</hi> he received; the <hi>ſweet words</hi> he uttered, <hi>Father forgive them,</hi> &amp;c. yet the Rocks were more Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate than the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>We.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saturday.</hi> Of our <hi>Saviours Burial. Nicodemus</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> his
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:53294:73"/>
Bleſſed Mother and St. <hi>Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lene,</hi> and ſome other Honourable and Holy Perſons were concerned in it. They waſh'd his Wounds with their holy Tears, and Embalmed his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with their Sighs and Prayers and Richeſt Odours. <hi>He made his Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher with the Rich and Honourable,</hi> but yet the malicious <hi>Jews</hi> ſealed the Stone, and ſet a Watch to prevent, if poſſible, his riſing again to Glory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sunday.</hi> Of our Saviour's <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, Aſcenſion, and ſending of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> 1. The manner of his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. His Converſing Fourty days upon Earth, Comforting his Freinds, Strengthening his Diſciples, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them charge over his Flock. 2. his Aſcention into Heaven, ſiting on the right hand of God, that our Hearts and Affections might thither alſo aſcend. 3. His ſending the Holy Ghoſt on the Day of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> his Diſciples having Faſted, Watch'd and Pray'd continually day and night for ten days before. <hi>Reflect.</hi> His
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:53294:73"/>
Reſurrection the firſt Fruits and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of ours. His Aſcenſion to draw us and our affections after him. His ſending the Holy Ghoſt that the ſame Spirit that raiſed up him the Head, might alſo quicken us his Members.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:53294:74"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV. Meditations</hi> for the fifth Week.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MOnday.</hi> Of the <hi>Nobility of the Soul.</hi> 1. Created by God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his own Image. 2. God giveth his Angels Charge over it. As the Hills ſtand about <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſo ſtandeth the Lord round about <hi>them</hi> that fear him. 3. Of ſo great value is the Soul that our Saviour left the Boſom of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to redeem it, even with the price of his Blood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tueſday.</hi> Of a <hi>pure Conſcience,</hi> a right <hi>Faith,</hi> and doing <hi>all things</hi> for God's Honour. Theſe <hi>Three</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute the good Chriſtian, for the Life we now live is by Faith. <hi>And the pure in heart ſhall ſee God;</hi> ſhall have a
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:53294:74"/>
clear and more naked perception of him even in this Life. No Image or Idea can repreſent a Spirit, ſuch as God is. He is Purity it ſelf, percep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible only to the pure in Heart after an ineffable manner, and void of all ſenſible Idea's. <hi>Reflect.</hi> The purging therefore our Conſciences is to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully minded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> Of the <hi>Preſence of God.</hi> With the thoughts of this ſo great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, many holy Perſons have preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v'd themſelves from ſin. <hi>Enoch</hi> walked <hi>with God</hi> and was tranſlated. <hi>Abraham</hi> walked <hi>before God</hi> and was perfect. King <hi>David</hi> ſet God always <hi>before him,</hi> that he ſhould not ſin. So <hi>Elijah</hi> and <hi>Eliſha, God liveth, in whoſe ſight and preſence I ſtand.</hi> And nothing more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain than that God filleth and worketh in all his Creatures. In him we <hi>live</hi> and <hi>move</hi> and have our <hi>being,</hi> and all things ſubſiſt and are upheld by his immediate hand. But he more nearly dwells and inhabits in every good Man, and directs him by the Interiour Language
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:53294:75"/>
of his Inſpirations and gives him leave alſo to Communicate to him as to a moſt faithful Freind all his Wants, Deſires, Reſolutions, Infirmities, Temptations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the oftner he recollects his Faculties from external objects, and retireth into himſelf to God ſo much the better, and his progreſs in holineſs greater and more eaſy. <hi>Reflect.</hi> How great a folly therefore is it to live inſenſible of the Aſſiſtance of ſo great a preſence ſo near us, even within us!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thurſday.</hi> Of the <hi>Conjunction of the Soul with God.</hi> Which conſiſts in a Conformity of our <hi>Will</hi> to the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.</hi> We muſt <hi>Will</hi> the ſame thing with God and the ſame means to it. <hi>My Son give me thy heart,</hi> ſays God by <hi>Solomon. It is good for me to cleave to God,</hi> ſays <hi>David.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul nothing could. ſeparate from Chriſt: Neither Life, nor Death, &amp;c.</hi> 2. Such a Perſon is always Examining his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, Keep's a ſtrict guard that his thoughts wander not abroad, or be
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:53294:75"/>
over long buſied in outward Affairs, for fear of loſing that preſence, that Conſolation he always carries about with him in his Soul. Prayers, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, Contemplation, Recollecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Holy Sacraments, are in a manner the entertainment of his whole Life. <hi>Reflect.</hi> All theſe things are irkſome and nauſeous to the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, Worldly Man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friday,</hi> Of <hi>Humility.</hi> 1. The <hi>Humble man</hi> retains a true ſence of God's Favours. What great things he hath both done and ſuffered for him, and that out of a free and moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazingly generous Goodneſs, without any the leaſt merit on his ſide. And on the contrary what returns he hath made, how many and how great wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſes committed againſt that good God. So that he knows not which way to turn himſelf: Thinks no place vile enough for <hi>him,</hi> who for his ſins de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the greateſt Afflictions, the greateſt Torments. He hath no way but to <hi>humble</hi> himſelf before God,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:53294:76"/>
with Confuſion of Face, and Offer and Reſign himſelf wholly to his boundleſs Mercy, to deal with him as his Compaſſion pleaſes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The true <hi>Humble Man</hi> is Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of all; Eſpecially his lawful Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours and Teachers, to whoſe wiſer Judgment he readily ſubmits his own leſs wiſe: As knowing they have more ability to judge than himſelf, and more aſſiſtance alſo promiſed not to miſtake. To theſe therefore he ſubmits as to Chriſt himſelf, being commanded ſo to do; <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.7, 8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly. Being contemned he rejoiceth; being honoured he referrs the <hi>honour</hi> to God, and ſo all other Benefits he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives. But the <hi>ſhame</hi> of his ſins he takes to himſelf; and confeſſes with the poor <hi>Publican</hi> that he is not <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> to lift up his eyes to Heaven.</p>
               <p n="4">4ly. What humilty can equal that of our Lord in all his whole Life, and who alſo humbled himſelf to death, even the death of the Croſs? And we
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:53294:76"/>
are to be like him, meek and humble. <hi>Reflect.</hi> The undeſerved <hi>Favours</hi> of Almighty God. The Ingratitude of our repeated ſins. The behaviour of the poor <hi>Publican.</hi> The Example of our <hi>Lord</hi> himſelf. Great Leſſons of Humility.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday.</hi> Of the <hi>Advantage of being Chriſtians.</hi> We live under the Covenant of Grace, which is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Remiſſion of ſin, and upon promiſes of eternal rewards to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers of it, who are alſo enabled to obſerve it. We are redeemed from all our Enemies ſo as not to fear them: Death it ſelf being now only a Paſſage to immortality. Are we not alſo made <hi>Sons of God, Members of Chriſt, Kings</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heirs</hi> with our Elder Brother of an Eternal Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sunday.</hi> Of the <hi>Benefits of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> By him (who was ſent by our Saviour) we are <hi>begotten</hi> and <hi>born again</hi> and made <hi>new creatures.</hi> By him <hi>Illuminated</hi> to underſtand the Myſteries of our Redemption. By
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:53294:77"/>
him the <hi>Love of God</hi> is ſpread abroad in our hearts, ſo as to love even our <hi>Enemies</hi> for God's ſake. He <hi>purifies</hi> and <hi>cleanſes</hi> us from all filthineſs. He <hi>Interceeds</hi> for us and teaches us how to <hi>pray.</hi> He <hi>comforts</hi> and <hi>ſupports</hi> us in all our afflictions with his <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>joy.</hi> He is the Seal of the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and the <hi>Foretaſte</hi> of Heaven. The <hi>great power of God in us,</hi> over Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can and all his Inſtruments. And by his Vertue and Efficacy, our <hi>Bodies</hi> alſo will be Spiritualized and we raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Immortality and Glory. <hi>Reflect.</hi> This Comforter abides with us for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and is grieved when-ever we do any thing to chaſe him from us.</p>
               <p>To theſe few <hi>Heads of Meditation</hi> (taken chiefly out of Holy Scripture) might be added infinite more concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>God's Attributes, Gifts, Miracles, &amp;c.</hi> with innumerable more paſſages both of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> but <hi>theſe</hi> are thought ſufficient to ſhew the manner of <hi>Meditation</hi> (which is ſo conſiderable a part of Religion)
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:53294:77"/>
and to ſerve alſo as a <hi>Succidaneum</hi> to thoſe that have not the opportunity of larger Books, which is all that was intended by the Collecter of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let the words of my Mouth and the Meditation of my heart be acceptable in thy ſight, O Lord, my Strength and my Redeemer,</hi> Pſal. 19.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I meditate on all thy works,</hi> Pſ. 143.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In his Law doth he meditate day and night,</hi> Pſ. 1.2.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="litany">
            <pb facs="tcp:53294:78"/>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:53294:78"/>
            <head>The Letany of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Vertues, taken out of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and the ſeveral Texts Annexed.</head>
            <p>O GOD the Father of Heaven,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O God the Son, Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the World,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O God the Holy Ghoſt,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Sacred Trinity, one God,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Lord juſt and good,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6</note> and a rewarder of all thoſe that ſeek thee diligently;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who createdſt our Firſt Parents in Innocency and Holineſs,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> after thine own Image; and gaveſt a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:53294:79"/>
to the offerings of juſt <hi>Abel;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who ſavedſt in the <hi>Ark</hi> from the Flood,<note place="margin">Gen. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Noah,</hi> a Preacher of Juſtice; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liveredſt from the Fire Juſt <hi>Lot</hi> vexed with the filthy Converſation of the wicked;<note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who gaveſt the Promiſe to <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 22.</note> found Faithful after many tryals;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 29.</note>Who deliveredſt <hi>Jacob,</hi> endued with a wonderful pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and confidence in Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, from all evils; and gaveſt a joyful end to thy Servant <hi>Job,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 42.</note> that Pattern of Patience;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 39.</note>Who rewardedſt the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Modeſty and Chaſtity of <hi>Joſeph</hi> with the Rule over <hi>Egypt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 41:</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Num. 22.</note>Who choſedſt <hi>Moſes</hi> the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:53294:79"/>
meekeſt Man upon Earth to be Ruler over thy People; and Electedſt <hi>Joſhua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 31.</note> notable for Valour and Conſtancy, to lead thy People into the Land of Promiſe;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who gaveſt the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to the Sons of <hi>Levi</hi> for their great Courage in vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating thine Honour;<note place="margin">Exod. 32.</note> and deliveredſt from all dangers the Prophet <hi>Elias</hi> for his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Zeal for thy true Worſhip againſt the falſe Prophets;<note place="margin">1 King. 18.</note> 
               <note place="margin">2 King. 2.</note> and at length tokeſt him up into Heaven;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who ſet <hi>Samuel</hi> Judge over thy People,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 7 12</note> a lover of Juſtice, and free from Bribes: And liftedſt up <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 16.</note> a man after thine own heart, in the faithful Service of thee, to be King of <hi>Iſrael;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who repleniſhedſt <hi>Solomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 4.</note> humbly begging Wiſdom of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:53294:80"/>
thee both with it and many other Graces: And Adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edſt <hi>Daniel</hi> and his Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">Dan. 1.</note> being ſingularly Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and Sober, with Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Beauty;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who didſt chuſe the Bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1.</note> Adorned with ſingular Chaſtity, Humility, Obedience, and all other Vertues, to be the Mother of thy Son;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3.</note>Who ſenteſt <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> a Forerunner of thy Son, a Preacher of Penitence, and of great Auſterities and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinencies;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">John. 17. 1 Pet. 2.21.</note>Who ſenteſt Jeſus Chriſt, thy only begotten Son into the World, the Pattern of all Holineſs, that we ſhould follow his Example;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 1.</note>Who haſt choſen us in
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:53294:80"/>
him before the Foundations of the World, that we alſo ſhould be Holy and Unblame able in thy ſight;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who haſt Predeſtinated us that we ſhould be made conformable to the Image of thy Son;<note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2.</note> and haſt created us in him to good Works, which thou haſt ordained that we ſhould walk in them;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who haſt Redeemed us from our vain Converſation by the precious Blood of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.</note> and haſt Regenerat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us by thy Word unto a lively hope of an Eternal Inheritance;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Jeſu,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.</note> who kneweſt no Sin neither was Guile found in thy Mouth,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.</note> but appearedſt to take away the Sins of the World;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:53294:81"/>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.</note>Jeſus who bareſt our Sins in thy Body on the Croſs, that we being dead unto Sin, may live unto Juſtice and Holineſs;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.</note>Who haſt delivered us out of Darkneſs into Light, from the power of Satan,<note place="margin">Acts 26.</note> into thy Kingdom, and haſt beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon us the Remiſſion of Sins and an Inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thy Saints;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 19.</note>Who promiſedſt thy Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that forſook all, for thee,<note place="margin">Joh. 21.</note> Twelve Thrones Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> who committedſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> notably confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and loving thee, the feeding of thy Sheep;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 20.</note>Who vouchſafedſt to St. <hi>John</hi> notable for Chaſtity, the ſingular privilege of thy Love; <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:53294:81"/>Who ſendeſt thy Holy Spirit,<note place="margin">Rom.</note> whereby Divine Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is ſpread abroad in our hearts:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have mercy on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be merciful, and ſpare us, O Lord:</p>
            <p>Be merciful, and grant un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, O Lord,</p>
            <p>The Vertue of Humility,<note place="margin">Mat. 18, Luk. 21, Mark 5. Heb. 13.</note> and Patience; Spiritual Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and Meekneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganimity and obedience to thoſe that are ſet over us:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grant unto us, O Lord,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A quiet mind and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with our preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dition,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. Heb. 13. Rom. 14.</note> true peace and joy in the Holy Ghoſt:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grant unto us O Lord,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Temperance and Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty;<note place="margin">Gal. 5. 1 Tim. 2.</note> Sobriety and Chaſtity; a true love of Thee and our Neigbours;<note place="margin">Mat. 22.38</note> the Contempt of our ſelves and the things of this World,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6 17 2 Cor. 9.</note> Bounty and
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:53294:82"/>
Compaſſionate Affections:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.8.</note>
               <hi>Grant unto us, O Lord,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diligence and conſtant Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilancy;<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.5. 1 Pet. 4.7. Mat. 5.6. 1 Cor. 7.11 Acts 28.15 Mat. 10.22</note> a Hunger and Thirſt after Holineſs: Zeal and Fervour of Spirit; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Fortitude and Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to the End;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grant unto us, O Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We Sinners beſeech thee to hear us, O Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom, 5.10.</note>That being reconciled to God,<note place="margin">Col. 1.20.</note> by the death of Chriſt, we may preſent our ſelves Holy,<note place="margin">Jam. 1.</note> Unſpotted, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blamable before him, that we may walk worthy of God,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.12</note> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.18.</note> in all things well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, fruitful in good works, and encreaſing in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God;<note place="margin">Col. 1, 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We Sinners beſeech thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.10.</note>That whatſoever we do in word or deed, we may do all to the Glory of God; that we make not void thy Grace,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2, 21</note> or receive it in vain;</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:53294:82"/>
               <hi>We Sinners beſeech thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That we be careful to ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in our hearts,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.15</note> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.21.</note> that we ſeek not our own things, but, before all, the things of Jeſus Chriſt;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We Sinners beſeech thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That looking up to Jeſus who ſuffered,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.2, 3.</note> we be not wearied and faint in our minds;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.11</note> but conſidering the Converſation of the Saints, imitate their Faith and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We Sinners beſeech thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That as Souldiers we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle not our ſelves in the things of this World;<note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.15</note> but having Food and Rayment let us be content therewith;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We Sinners beſeech thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That by good Works we make our Faith and Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſure;<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.10</note> that we do good whilſt we have time,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.9.</note> and faint not, for that we ſhall reap in due ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:53294:83"/>
               <hi>We Sinners beſeech thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That we forbear one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in love,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.2.</note> being careful to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace;<note place="margin">Gal. 6.2.</note> that we bear one anothers burthens and ſo fulfill the law of God;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We Sinners beſeech thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That being Strengthned in all Vertue through the power of his Grace,<note place="margin">Col. 1.11.</note> we give thanks to God with all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and Longſuffering;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We Sinners beſeech thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.14.</note>That waiting for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Lord, we be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to be found in him pure and unſpotted in Peace,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.9.</note> that we may receive the end of our Faith, even the Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Souls; and in the mean time work out our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling;<note place="margin">Phil 12.12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We Sinners beſeech thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>O Lamb of God, that takeſt away the ſins of the
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:53294:83"/>
World, increaſe our Faith.</p>
            <p>O Lamb of God that tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt away the ſins of the World, infuſe Hope.</p>
            <p>O Lamb of God, that tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt away the ſins of the World, enkindle Charity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Father which art in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Let us Pray.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> God, who juſtifieſt the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, we humbly beſeech thy Majeſty Graciouſly to defend with thy Heavenly Grace, and aſſiſt with thy continual Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, us thy Servants, relying on thy Mercy; that, conſtantly running in the Courſe of Vertue, we may at length receive the Crown thereof, and by no Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations be withdrawn from ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee; through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Ame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:53294:84"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. Line 4. Almighty God,. P. 27. l. 7. many. p. 29. l. 5. Primo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geneal. P. 34. l. 4. Bleſſings. P. 38. l. 19. but that. P. 40. l. 19. Fig-leaves. P. 43. l. 9. <hi>deteriora &amp;c.</hi> P. 74. l 15. plainly. P. 92. l. 21. Rational into Natural. l. 23. Natural into Carnal. P. 98. l. 21. frequent. P. 103. l. 1. cheriſh. P. 118. l. 21 exquiſite Tortures. l. 23. Almighty.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:53294:84"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
